Channels

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the introductory guides and got a Phoenix application up and running.

Channels are an exciting part of Phoenix that enable soft real-time communication with and between millions of connected clients.

Some possible use cases include:

Chat rooms and APIs for messaging apps
Breaking news, like "a goal was scored" or "an earthquake is coming"
Tracking trains, trucks, or race participants on a map
Events in multiplayer games
Monitoring sensors and controlling lights
Notifying a browser that a page's CSS or JavaScript has changed (this is handy in development)

Conceptually, Channels are pretty simple.

First, clients connect to the server using some transport, like WebSocket. Once connected, they join one or more topics. For example, to interact with a public chat room clients may join a topic called public_chat, and to receive updates from a product with ID 7, they may need to join a topic called product_updates:7.

Clients can push messages to the topics they've joined, and can also receive messages from them. The other way around, Channel servers receive messages from their connected clients, and can push messages to them too.

Servers are able to broadcast messages to all clients subscribed to a certain topic. This is illustrated in the following diagram:

                                                                  +----------------+
                                                     +--Topic X-->| Mobile Client  |
                                                     |            +----------------+
                              +-------------------+  |
+----------------+            |                   |  |            +----------------+
| Browser Client |--Topic X-->| Phoenix Server(s) |--+--Topic X-->| Desktop Client |
+----------------+            |                   |  |            +----------------+
                              +-------------------+  |
                                                     |            +----------------+
                                                     +--Topic X-->|   IoT Client   |
                                                                  +----------------+

Broadcasts work even if the application runs on several nodes/computers. That is, if two clients have their socket connected to different application nodes and are subscribed to the same topic T, both of them will receive messages broadcasted to T. That is possible thanks to an internal PubSub mechanism.

Channels can support any kind of client: a browser, native app, smart watch, embedded device, or anything else that can connect to a network. All the client needs is a suitable library; see the Client Libraries section below. Each client library communicates using one of the "transports" that Channels understand. Currently, that's either Websockets or long polling, but other transports may be added in the future.

Unlike stateless HTTP connections, Channels support long-lived connections, each backed by a lightweight BEAM process, working in parallel and maintaining its own state.

This architecture scales well; Phoenix Channels can support millions of subscribers with reasonable latency on a single box, passing hundreds of thousands of messages per second. And that capacity can be multiplied by adding more nodes to the cluster.

The Moving Parts

Although Channels are simple to use from a client perspective, there are a number of components involved in routing messages to clients across a cluster of servers. Let's take a look at them.

Overview

To start communicating, a client connects to a node (a Phoenix server) using a transport (e.g., Websockets or long polling) and joins one or more channels using that single network connection. One channel server lightweight process is created per client, per topic. Each channel holds onto the %Phoenix.Socket{} and can maintain any state it needs within its socket.assigns.

Once the connection is established, each incoming message from a client is routed, based on its topic, to the correct channel server. If the channel server asks to broadcast a message, that message is sent to the local PubSub, which sends it out to any clients connected to the same server and subscribed to that topic.

If there are other nodes in the cluster, the local PubSub also forwards the message to their PubSubs, which send it out to their own subscribers. Because only one message has to be sent per additional node, the performance cost of adding nodes is negligible, while each new node supports many more subscribers.

The message flow looks something like this:

                                 Channel   +-------------------------+      +--------+
                                  route    | Sending Client, Topic 1 |      | Local  |
                              +----------->|     Channel.Server      |----->| PubSub |--+
+----------------+            |            +-------------------------+      +--------+  |
| Sending Client |-Transport--+                                                  |      |
+----------------+                         +-------------------------+           |      |
                                           | Sending Client, Topic 2 |           |      |
                                           |     Channel.Server      |           |      |
                                           +-------------------------+           |      |
                                                                                 |      |
                                           +-------------------------+           |      |
+----------------+                         | Browser Client, Topic 1 |           |      |
| Browser Client |<-------Transport--------|     Channel.Server      |<----------+      |
+----------------+                         +-------------------------+                  |
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |
                                           +-------------------------+                  |
+----------------+                         |  Phone Client, Topic 1  |                  |
|  Phone Client  |<-------Transport--------|     Channel.Server      |<-+               |
+----------------+                         +-------------------------+  |   +--------+  |
                                                                        |   | Remote |  |
                                           +-------------------------+  +---| PubSub |<-+
+----------------+                         |  Watch Client, Topic 1  |  |   +--------+  |
|  Watch Client  |<-------Transport--------|     Channel.Server      |<-+               |
+----------------+                         +-------------------------+                  |
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |
                                           +-------------------------+      +--------+  |
+----------------+                         |   IoT Client, Topic 1   |      | Remote |  |
|   IoT Client   |<-------Transport--------|     Channel.Server      |<-----| PubSub |<-+
+----------------+                         +-------------------------+      +--------+

Endpoint

In your Phoenix app's Endpoint module, a socket declaration specifies which socket handler will receive connections on a given URL.

socket "/socket", HelloWeb.UserSocket,
  websocket: true,
  longpoll: false

Phoenix comes with two default transports: websocket and longpoll. You can configure them directly via the socket declaration.

Socket Handlers

On the client side, you will establish a socket connection to the route above:

let socket = new Socket("/socket", {params: {token: window.userToken}})

On the server, Phoenix will invoke HelloWeb.UserSocket.connect/2, passing your parameters and the initial socket state. Within the socket, you can authenticate and identify a socket connection and set default socket assigns. The socket is also where you define your channel routes.

Channel Routes

Channel routes match on the topic string and dispatch matching requests to the given Channel module.

The star character * acts as a wildcard matcher, so in the following example route, requests for room:lobby and room:123 would both be dispatched to the RoomChannel. In your UserSocket, you would have:

channel "room:*", HelloWeb.RoomChannel

Channels

Channels handle events from clients, so they are similar to Controllers, but there are two key differences. Channel events can go both directions - incoming and outgoing. Channel connections also persist beyond a single request/response cycle. Channels are the highest level abstraction for real-time communication components in Phoenix.

Each Channel will implement one or more clauses of each of these four callback functions - join/3, terminate/2, handle_in/3, and handle_out/3.

Topics

Topics are string identifiers - names that the various layers use in order to make sure messages end up in the right place. As we saw above, topics can use wildcards. This allows for a useful "topic:subtopic" convention. Often, you'll compose topics using record IDs from your application layer, such as "users:123".

Messages

The Phoenix.Socket.Message module defines a struct with the following keys which denotes a valid message. From the Phoenix.Socket.Message docs.

topic - The string topic or "topic:subtopic" pair namespace, such as "messages" or "messages:123"
event - The string event name, for example "phx_join"
payload - The message payload
ref - The unique string ref

PubSub

PubSub is provided by the Phoenix.PubSub module. Interested parties can receive events by subscribing to topics. Other processes can broadcast events to certain topics.

This is useful to broadcast messages on channel and also for application development in general. For instance, letting all connected live views to know that a new comment has been added to a post.

The PubSub system takes care of getting messages from one node to another so that they can be sent to all subscribers across the cluster. By default, this is done using Phoenix.PubSub.PG2, which uses native BEAM messaging.

If your deployment environment does not support distributed Elixir or direct communication between servers, Phoenix also ships with a Redis Adapter that uses Redis to exchange PubSub data. Please see the Phoenix.PubSub docs for more information.

Client Libraries

Any networked device can connect to Phoenix Channels as long as it has a client library. The following libraries exist today, and new ones are always welcome; to write your own, see our how-to guide Writing a Channels Client.

Official

Phoenix ships with a JavaScript client that is available when generating a new Phoenix project. The documentation for the JavaScript module is available at https://hexdocs.pm/phoenix/js/; the code is in multiple js files.

3rd Party

Swift (iOS)

SwiftPhoenix

Java (Android)

JavaPhoenixChannels

Kotlin (Android)

JavaPhoenixClient

C#

PhoenixSharp

Elixir

phoenix_gen_socket_client
slipstream

GDScript (Godot Game Engine)

GodotPhoenixChannels

Tying it all together

Let's tie all these ideas together by building a simple chat application. Make sure you created a new Phoenix application and now we are ready to generate the UserSocket.

Generating a socket

Let's invoke the socket generator to get started:

$ mix phx.gen.socket User

It will create two files, the client code in assets/js/user_socket.js and the server counter-part in lib/hello_web/channels/user_socket.ex. After running, the generator will also ask to add the following line to lib/hello_web/endpoint.ex:

defmodule HelloWeb.Endpoint do
  use Phoenix.Endpoint, otp_app: :hello

  socket "/socket", HelloWeb.UserSocket,
    websocket: true,
    longpoll: false

  ...
end

The generator also asks us to import the client code, we will do that later.

Next, we will configure our socket to ensure messages get routed to the correct channel. To do that, we'll uncomment the "room:*" channel definition:

defmodule HelloWeb.UserSocket do
  use Phoenix.Socket

  ## Channels
  channel "room:*", HelloWeb.RoomChannel
  ...

Now, whenever a client sends a message whose topic starts with "room:", it will be routed to our RoomChannel. Next, we'll define a HelloWeb.RoomChannel module to manage our chat room messages.

Joining Channels

The first priority of your channels is to authorize clients to join a given topic. For authorization, we must implement join/3 in lib/hello_web/channels/room_channel.ex.

defmodule HelloWeb.RoomChannel do
  use Phoenix.Channel

  def join("room:lobby", _message, socket) do
    {:ok, socket}
  end

  def join("room:" <> _private_room_id, _params, _socket) do
    {:error, %{reason: "unauthorized"}}
  end
end

For our chat app, we'll allow anyone to join the "room:lobby" topic, but any other room will be considered private and special authorization, say from a database, will be required. (We won't worry about private chat rooms for this exercise, but feel free to explore after we finish.)

With our channel in place, let's get the client and server talking.

The generated assets/js/user_socket.js defines a simple client based on the socket implementation that ships with Phoenix.

We can use that library to connect to our socket and join our channel, we just need to set our room name to "room:lobby" in that file.

// assets/js/user_socket.js
// ...
socket.connect()

// Now that you are connected, you can join channels with a topic:
let channel = socket.channel("room:lobby", {})
channel.join()
  .receive("ok", resp => { console.log("Joined successfully", resp) })
  .receive("error", resp => { console.log("Unable to join", resp) })

export default socket

After that, we need to make sure assets/js/user_socket.js gets imported into our application JavaScript file. To do that, uncomment this line in assets/js/app.js.

// ...
import "./user_socket.js"

Save the file and your browser should auto refresh, thanks to the Phoenix live reloader. If everything worked, we should see "Joined successfully" in the browser's JavaScript console. Our client and server are now talking over a persistent connection. Now let's make it useful by enabling chat.

In lib/hello_web/controllers/page_html/home.html.heex, we'll replace the existing code with a container to hold our chat messages, and an input field to send them:

<div id="messages" role="log" aria-live="polite"></div>
<input id="chat-input" type="text">

Now let's add a couple of event listeners to assets/js/user_socket.js:

// ...
let channel           = socket.channel("room:lobby", {})
let chatInput         = document.querySelector("#chat-input")
let messagesContainer = document.querySelector("#messages")

chatInput.addEventListener("keypress", event => {
  if(event.key === 'Enter'){
    channel.push("new_msg", {body: chatInput.value})
    chatInput.value = ""
  }
})

channel.join()
  .receive("ok", resp => { console.log("Joined successfully", resp) })
  .receive("error", resp => { console.log("Unable to join", resp) })

export default socket

All we had to do is detect that enter was pressed and then push an event over the channel with the message body. We named the event "new_msg". With this in place, let's handle the other piece of a chat application, where we listen for new messages and append them to our messages container.

// ...
let channel           = socket.channel("room:lobby", {})
let chatInput         = document.querySelector("#chat-input")
let messagesContainer = document.querySelector("#messages")

chatInput.addEventListener("keypress", event => {
  if(event.key === 'Enter'){
    channel.push("new_msg", {body: chatInput.value})
    chatInput.value = ""
  }
})

channel.on("new_msg", payload => {
  let messageItem = document.createElement("p")
  messageItem.innerText = `[${Date()}] ${payload.body}`
  messagesContainer.appendChild(messageItem)
})

channel.join()
  .receive("ok", resp => { console.log("Joined successfully", resp) })
  .receive("error", resp => { console.log("Unable to join", resp) })

export default socket

We listen for the "new_msg" event using channel.on, and then append the message body to the DOM. Now let's handle the incoming and outgoing events on the server to complete the picture.

Incoming Events

We handle incoming events with handle_in/3. We can pattern match on the event names, like "new_msg", and then grab the payload that the client passed over the channel. For our chat application, we simply need to notify all other room:lobby subscribers of the new message with broadcast!/3.

defmodule HelloWeb.RoomChannel do
  use Phoenix.Channel

  def join("room:lobby", _message, socket) do
    {:ok, socket}
  end

  def join("room:" <> _private_room_id, _params, _socket) do
    {:error, %{reason: "unauthorized"}}
  end

  def handle_in("new_msg", %{"body" => body}, socket) do
    broadcast!(socket, "new_msg", %{body: body})
    {:noreply, socket}
  end
end

broadcast!/3 will notify all joined clients on this socket's topic and invoke their handle_out/3 callbacks. handle_out/3 isn't a required callback, but it allows us to customize and filter broadcasts before they reach each client. By default, handle_out/3 is implemented for us and simply pushes the message on to the client. Hooking into outgoing events allows for powerful message customization and filtering. Let's see how.

Intercepting Outgoing Events

We won't implement this for our application, but imagine our chat app allowed users to ignore messages about new users joining a room. We could implement that behavior like this, where we explicitly tell Phoenix which outgoing event we want to intercept and then define a handle_out/3 callback for those events. (Of course, this assumes that we have an Accounts context with an ignoring_user?/2 function, and that we pass a user in via the assigns map). It is important to note that the handle_out/3 callback will be called for every recipient of a message, so more expensive operations like hitting the database should be considered carefully before being included in handle_out/3.

intercept ["user_joined"]

def handle_out("user_joined", msg, socket) do
  if Accounts.ignoring_user?(socket.assigns[:user], msg.user_id) do
    {:noreply, socket}
  else
    push(socket, "user_joined", msg)
    {:noreply, socket}
  end
end

That's all there is to our basic chat app. Fire up multiple browser tabs and you should see your messages being pushed and broadcasted to all windows!

Using Token Authentication

When we connect, we'll often need to authenticate the client. Fortunately, this is a 4-step process with Phoenix.Token.

Step 1 - Assign a Token in the Connection

Let's say we have an authentication plug in our app called OurAuth. When OurAuth authenticates a user, it sets a value for the :current_user key in conn.assigns. Since the current_user exists, we can simply assign the user's token in the connection for use in the layout. We can wrap that behavior up in a private function plug, put_user_token/2. This could also be put in its own module as well. To make this all work, we just add OurAuth and put_user_token/2 to the browser pipeline.

pipeline :browser do
  ...
  plug OurAuth
  plug :put_user_token
end

defp put_user_token(conn, _) do
  if current_user = conn.assigns[:current_user] do
    token = Phoenix.Token.sign(conn, "user socket", current_user.id)
    assign(conn, :user_token, token)
  else
    conn
  end
end

Now our conn.assigns contains the current_user and user_token.

Step 2 - Pass the Token to the JavaScript

Next, we need to pass this token to JavaScript. We can do so inside a script tag in lib/hello_web/components/layouts/app.html.heex right above the app.js script, as follows:

<script>window.userToken = "<%= assigns[:user_token] %>";</script>
<script src={~p"/assets/app.js"}></script>

Step 3 - Pass the Token to the Socket Constructor and Verify

We also need to pass the :params to the socket constructor and verify the user token in the connect/3 function. To do so, edit lib/hello_web/channels/user_socket.ex, as follows:

def connect(%{"token" => token}, socket, _connect_info) do
  # max_age: 1209600 is equivalent to two weeks in seconds
  case Phoenix.Token.verify(socket, "user socket", token, max_age: 1209600) do
    {:ok, user_id} ->
      {:ok, assign(socket, :current_user, user_id)}
    {:error, reason} ->
      :error
  end
end

In our JavaScript, we can use the token set previously when constructing the Socket:

let socket = new Socket("/socket", {params: {token: window.userToken}})

We used Phoenix.Token.verify/4 to verify the user token provided by the client. Phoenix.Token.verify/4 returns either {:ok, user_id} or {:error, reason}. We can pattern match on that return in a case statement. With a verified token, we set the user's id as the value to :current_user in the socket. Otherwise, we return :error.

Step 4 - Connect to the socket in JavaScript

With authentication set up, we can connect to sockets and channels from JavaScript.

let socket = new Socket("/socket", {params: {token: window.userToken}})
socket.connect()

Now that we are connected, we can join channels with a topic:

let channel = socket.channel("topic:subtopic", {})
channel.join()
  .receive("ok", resp => { console.log("Joined successfully", resp) })
  .receive("error", resp => { console.log("Unable to join", resp) })

export default socket

Note that token authentication is preferable since it's transport agnostic and well-suited for long running-connections like channels, as opposed to using sessions or other authentication approaches.

Fault Tolerance and Reliability Guarantees

Servers restart, networks split, and clients lose connectivity. In order to design robust systems, we need to understand how Phoenix responds to these events and what guarantees it offers.

Handling Reconnection

Clients subscribe to topics, and Phoenix stores those subscriptions in an in-memory ETS table. If a channel crashes, the clients will need to reconnect to the topics they had previously subscribed to. Fortunately, the Phoenix JavaScript client knows how to do this. The server will notify all the clients of the crash. This will trigger each client's Channel.onError callback. The clients will attempt to reconnect to the server using an exponential backoff strategy. Once they reconnect, they'll attempt to rejoin the topics they had previously subscribed to. If they are successful, they'll start receiving messages from those topics as before.

Resending Client Messages

Channel clients queue outgoing messages into a PushBuffer, and send them to the server when there is a connection. If no connection is available, the client holds on to the messages until it can establish a new connection. With no connection, the client will hold the messages in memory until it establishes a connection, or until it receives a timeout event. The default timeout is set to 5000 milliseconds. The client won't persist the messages in the browser's local storage, so if the browser tab closes, the messages will be gone.

Resending Server Messages

Phoenix uses an at-most-once strategy when sending messages to clients. If the client is offline and misses the message, Phoenix won't resend it. Phoenix doesn't persist messages on the server. If the server restarts, unsent messages will be gone. If our application needs stronger guarantees around message delivery, we'll need to write that code ourselves. Common approaches involve persisting messages on the server and having clients request missing messages. For an example, see Chris McCord's Phoenix training: client code and server code.

Example Application

To see an example of the application we just built, checkout the project phoenix_chat_example.

Contexts

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the introductory guides and got a Phoenix application up and running.

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the Request life-cycle guide.

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the Ecto guide.

So far, we've built pages, wired up controller actions through our routers, and learned how Ecto allows data to be validated and persisted. Now it's time to tie it all together by writing web-facing features that interact with our greater Elixir application.

When building a Phoenix project, we are first and foremost building an Elixir application. Phoenix's job is to provide a web interface into our Elixir application. Naturally, we compose our applications with modules and functions, but we often assign specific responsibilities to certain modules and give them names: such as controllers, routers, and live views.

As everything else, contexts in Phoenix are modules, but with the distinct reponsibility of drawing boundaries and grouping functionality. In other words, they allow us to reason and discuss about application design.

Thinking about contexts

Contexts are dedicated modules that expose and group related functionality. For example, anytime you call Elixir's standard library, be it Logger.info/1 or Stream.map/2, you are accessing different contexts. Internally, Elixir's logger is made of multiple modules, but we never interact with those modules directly. We call the Logger module the context, exactly because it exposes and groups all of the logging functionality.

By giving modules that expose and group related functionality the name contexts, we help developers identify these patterns and talk about them. At the end of the day, contexts are just modules, as are your controllers, views, etc.

In Phoenix, contexts often encapsulate data access and data validation. They often talk to a database or APIs. Overall, think of them as boundaries to decouple and isolate parts of your application. Let's use these ideas to build out our web application. Our goal is to build an ecommerce system where we can showcase products, allow users to add products to their cart, and complete their orders.

How to read this guide: Using the context generators is a great way for beginners and intermediate Elixir programmers alike to get up and running quickly while thoughtfully writing their applications. This guide focuses on those readers.

Adding a Catalog Context

An ecommerce platform has wide-reaching coupling across a codebase so it's important to think about writing well-defined modules. With that in mind, our goal is to build a product catalog API that handles creating, updating, and deleting the products available in our system. We'll start off with the basic features of showcasing our products, and we will add shopping cart features later. We'll see how starting with a solid foundation with isolated boundaries allows us to grow our application naturally as we add functionality.

Phoenix includes the mix phx.gen.html, mix phx.gen.json, mix phx.gen.live, and mix phx.gen.context generators that apply the ideas of isolating functionality in our applications into contexts. These generators are a great way to hit the ground running while Phoenix nudges you in the right direction to grow your application. Let's put these tools to use for our new product catalog context.

In order to run the context generators, we need to come up with a module name that groups the related functionality that we're building. In the Ecto guide, we saw how we can use Changesets and Repos to validate and persist user schemas, but we didn't integrate this with our application at large. In fact, we didn't think about where a "user" in our application should live at all. Let's take a step back and think about the different parts of our system. We know that we'll have products to showcase on pages for sale, along with descriptions, pricing, etc. Along with selling products, we know we'll need to support carting, order checkout, and so on. While the products being purchased are related to the cart and checkout processes, showcasing a product and managing the exhibition of our products is distinctly different than tracking what a user has placed in their cart or how an order is placed. A Catalog context is a natural place for the management of our product details and the showcasing of those products we have for sale.

Naming things is hard

If you're stuck when trying to come up with a context name when the grouped functionality in your system isn't yet clear, you can simply use the plural form of the resource you're creating. For example, a Products context for managing products. As you grow your application and the parts of your system become clear, you can simply rename the context to a more refined one.

To jump-start our catalog context, we'll use mix phx.gen.html which creates a context module that wraps up Ecto access for creating, updating, and deleting products, along with web files like controllers and templates for the web interface into our context. Run the following command at your project root:

$ mix phx.gen.html Catalog Product products title:string \
description:string price:decimal views:integer

* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_controller.ex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/edit.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/index.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/new.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/show.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/product_form.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html.ex
* creating test/hello_web/controllers/product_controller_test.exs
* creating lib/hello/catalog/product.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210201185747_create_products.exs
* creating lib/hello/catalog.ex
* injecting lib/hello/catalog.ex
* creating test/hello/catalog_test.exs
* injecting test/hello/catalog_test.exs
* creating test/support/fixtures/catalog_fixtures.ex
* injecting test/support/fixtures/catalog_fixtures.ex

Add the resource to your browser scope in lib/hello_web/router.ex:

    resources "/products", ProductController


Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

Phoenix generated the web files as expected in lib/hello_web/. We can also see our context files were generated inside a lib/hello/catalog.ex file and our product schema in the directory of the same name. Note the difference between lib/hello and lib/hello_web. We have a Catalog module to serve as the public API for product catalog functionality, as well as a Catalog.Product struct, which is an Ecto schema for casting and validating product data. Phoenix also provided web and context tests for us, it also included test helpers for creating entities via the Hello.Catalog context, which we'll look at later. For now, let's follow the instructions and add the route according to the console instructions, in lib/hello_web/router.ex:

  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    get "/", PageController, :index
+   resources "/products", ProductController
  end

With the new route in place, Phoenix reminds us to update our repo by running mix ecto.migrate, but first we need to make a few tweaks to the generated migration in priv/repo/migrations/*_create_products.exs:

  def change do
    create table(:products) do
      add :title, :string
      add :description, :string
-     add :price, :decimal
+     add :price, :decimal, precision: 15, scale: 6, null: false
-     add :views, :integer
+     add :views, :integer, default: 0, null: false

      timestamps()
    end

We modified our price column to a specific precision of 15, scale of 6, along with a not-null constraint. This ensures we store currency with proper precision for any mathematical operations we may perform. Next, we added a default value and not-null constraint to our views count. With our changes in place, we're ready to migrate up our database. Let's do that now:

$ mix ecto.migrate
14:09:02.260 [info] == Running 20210201185747 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateProducts.change/0 forward

14:09:02.262 [info] create table products

14:09:02.273 [info] == Migrated 20210201185747 in 0.0s

Before we jump into the generated code, let's start the server with mix phx.server and visit http://localhost:4000/products. Let's follow the "New Product" link and click the "Save" button without providing any input. We should be greeted with the following output:

Oops, something went wrong! Please check the errors below.

When we submit the form, we can see all the validation errors inline with the inputs. Nice! Out of the box, the context generator included the schema fields in our form template and we can see our default validations for required inputs are in effect. Let's enter some example product data and resubmit the form:

Product created successfully.

Title: Metaprogramming Elixir
Description: Write Less Code, Get More Done (and Have Fun!)
Price: 15.000000
Views: 0

If we follow the "Back" link, we get a list of all products, which should contain the one we just created. Likewise, we can update this record or delete it. Now that we've seen how it works in the browser, it's time to take a look at the generated code.

Starting with generators

That little mix phx.gen.html command packed a surprising punch. We got a lot of functionality out-of-the-box for creating, updating, and deleting products in our catalog. This is far from a full-featured app, but remember, generators are first and foremost learning tools and a starting point for you to begin building real features. Code generation can't solve all your problems, but it will teach you the ins and outs of Phoenix and nudge you towards the proper mindset when designing your application.

Let's first check out the ProductController that was generated in lib/hello_web/controllers/product_controller.ex:

defmodule HelloWeb.ProductController do
  use HelloWeb, :controller

  alias Hello.Catalog
  alias Hello.Catalog.Product

  def index(conn, _params) do
    products = Catalog.list_products()
    render(conn, :index, products: products)
  end

  def new(conn, _params) do
    changeset = Catalog.change_product(%Product{})
    render(conn, :new, changeset: changeset)
  end

  def create(conn, %{"product" => product_params}) do
    case Catalog.create_product(product_params) do
      {:ok, product} ->
        conn
        |> put_flash(:info, "Product created successfully.")
        |> redirect(to: ~p"/products/#{product}")

      {:error, %Ecto.Changeset{} = changeset} ->
        render(conn, :new, changeset: changeset)
    end
  end

  def show(conn, %{"id" => id}) do
    product = Catalog.get_product!(id)
    render(conn, :show, product: product)
  end
  ...
end

We've seen how controllers work in our controller guide, so the code probably isn't too surprising. What is worth noticing is how our controller calls into the Catalog context. We can see that the index action fetches a list of products with Catalog.list_products/0, and how products are persisted in the create action with Catalog.create_product/1. We haven't yet looked at the catalog context, so we don't yet know how product fetching and creation is happening under the hood – but that's the point. Our Phoenix controller is the web interface into our greater application. It shouldn't be concerned with the details of how products are fetched from the database or persisted into storage. We only care about telling our application to perform some work for us. This is great because our business logic and storage details are decoupled from the web layer of our application. If we move to a full-text storage engine later for fetching products instead of a SQL query, our controller doesn't need to be changed. Likewise, we can reuse our context code from any other interface in our application, be it a channel, mix task, or long-running process importing CSV data.

In the case of our create action, when we successfully create a product, we use Phoenix.Controller.put_flash/3 to show a success message, and then we redirect to the router's product show page. Conversely, if Catalog.create_product/1 fails, we render our "new.html" template and pass along the Ecto changeset for the template to lift error messages from.

Next, let's dig deeper and check out our Catalog context in lib/hello/catalog.ex:

defmodule Hello.Catalog do
  @moduledoc """
  The Catalog context.
  """

  import Ecto.Query, warn: false
  alias Hello.Repo

  alias Hello.Catalog.Product

  @doc """
  Returns the list of products.

  ## Examples

      iex> list_products()
      [%Product{}, ...]

  """
  def list_products do
    Repo.all(Product)
  end
  ...
end

This module will be the public API for all product catalog functionality in our system. For example, in addition to product detail management, we may also handle product category classification and product variants for things like optional sizing, trims, etc. If we look at the list_products/0 function, we can see the private details of product fetching. And it's super simple. We have a call to Repo.all(Product). We saw how Ecto repo queries worked in the Ecto guide, so this call should look familiar. Our list_products function is a generalized function name specifying the intent of our code – namely to list products. The details of that intent where we use our Repo to fetch the products from our PostgreSQL database is hidden from our callers. This is a common theme we'll see re-iterated as we use the Phoenix generators. Phoenix will push us to think about where we have different responsibilities in our application, and then to wrap up those different areas behind well-named modules and functions that make the intent of our code clear, while encapsulating the details.

Now we know how data is fetched, but how are products persisted? Let's take a look at the Catalog.create_product/1 function:

  @doc """
  Creates a product.

  ## Examples

      iex> create_product(%{field: value})
      {:ok, %Product{}}

      iex> create_product(%{field: bad_value})
      {:error, %Ecto.Changeset{}}

  """
  def create_product(attrs \\ %{}) do
    %Product{}
    |> Product.changeset(attrs)
    |> Repo.insert()
  end

There's more documentation than code here, but a couple of things are important to highlight. First, we can see again that our Ecto Repo is used under the hood for database access. You probably also noticed the call to Product.changeset/2. We talked about changesets before, and now we see them in action in our context.

If we open up the Product schema in lib/hello/catalog/product.ex, it will look immediately familiar:

defmodule Hello.Catalog.Product do
  use Ecto.Schema
  import Ecto.Changeset

  schema "products" do
    field :description, :string
    field :price, :decimal
    field :title, :string
    field :views, :integer

    timestamps()
  end

  @doc false
  def changeset(product, attrs) do
    product
    |> cast(attrs, [:title, :description, :price, :views])
    |> validate_required([:title, :description, :price, :views])
  end
end

This is just what we saw before when we ran mix phx.gen.schema, except here we see a @doc false above our changeset/2 function. This tells us that while this function is publicly callable, it's not part of the public context API. Callers that build changesets do so via the context API. For example, Catalog.create_product/1 calls into our Product.changeset/2 to build the changeset from user input. Callers, such as our controller actions, do not access Product.changeset/2 directly. All interaction with our product changesets is done through the public Catalog context.

Adding Catalog functions

As we've seen, your context modules are dedicated modules that expose and group related functionality. Phoenix generates generic functions, such as list_products and update_product, but they only serve as a basis for you to grow your business logic and application from. Let's add one of the basic features of our catalog by tracking product page view count.

For any ecommerce system, the ability to track how many times a product page has been viewed is essential for marketing, suggestions, ranking, etc. While we could try to use the existing Catalog.update_product function, along the lines of Catalog.update_product(product, %{views: product.views + 1}), this would not only be prone to race conditions, but it would also require the caller to know too much about our Catalog system. To see why the race condition exists, let's walk through the possible execution of events:

Intuitively, you would assume the following events:

User 1 loads the product page with count of 13
User 1 saves the product page with count of 14
User 2 loads the product page with count of 14
User 2 saves the product page with count of 15

While in practice this would happen:

User 1 loads the product page with count of 13
User 2 loads the product page with count of 13
User 1 saves the product page with count of 14
User 2 saves the product page with count of 14

The race conditions would make this an unreliable way to update the existing table since multiple callers may be updating out of date view values. There's a better way.

Let's think of a function that describes what we want to accomplish. Here's how we would like to use it:

product = Catalog.inc_page_views(product)

That looks great. Our callers will have no confusion over what this function does, and we can wrap up the increment in an atomic operation to prevent race conditions.

Open up your catalog context (lib/hello/catalog.ex), and add this new function:

  def inc_page_views(%Product{} = product) do
    {1, [%Product{views: views}]} =
      from(p in Product, where: p.id == ^product.id, select: [:views])
      |> Repo.update_all(inc: [views: 1])

    put_in(product.views, views)
  end

We built a query for fetching the current product given its ID which we pass to Repo.update_all. Ecto's Repo.update_all allows us to perform batch updates against the database, and is perfect for atomically updating values, such as incrementing our views count. The result of the repo operation returns the number of updated records, along with the selected schema values specified by the select option. When we receive the new product views, we use put_in(product.views, views) to place the new view count within the product struct.

With our context function in place, let's make use of it in our product controller. Update your show action in lib/hello_web/controllers/product_controller.ex to call our new function:

  def show(conn, %{"id" => id}) do
    product =
      id
      |> Catalog.get_product!()
      |> Catalog.inc_page_views()

    render(conn, :show, product: product)
  end

We modified our show action to pipe our fetched product into Catalog.inc_page_views/1, which will return the updated product. Then we rendered our template just as before. Let's try it out. Refresh one of your product pages a few times and watch the view count increase.

We can also see our atomic update in action in the ecto debug logs:

[debug] QUERY OK source="products" db=0.5ms idle=834.5ms
UPDATE "products" AS p0 SET "views" = p0."views" + $1 WHERE (p0."id" = $2) RETURNING p0."views" [1, 1]

Good work!

As we've seen, designing with contexts gives you a solid foundation to grow your application from. Using discrete, well-defined APIs that expose the intent of your system allows you to write more maintainable applications with reusable code. Now that we know how to start extending our context API, lets explore handling relationships within a context.

In-context relationships

Our basic catalog features are nice, but let's take it up a notch by categorizing products. Many ecommerce solutions allow products to be categorized in different ways, such as a product being marked for fashion, power tools, and so on. Starting with a one-to-one relationship between product and categories will cause major code changes later if we need to start supporting multiple categories. Let's set up a category association that will allow us to start off tracking a single category per product, but easily support more later as we grow our features.

For now, categories will contain only textual information. Our first order of business is to decide where categories live in the application. We have our Catalog context, which manages the exhibition of our products. Product categorization is a natural fit here. Phoenix is also smart enough to generate code inside an existing context, which makes adding new resources to a context a breeze. Run the following command at your project root:

Sometimes it may be tricky to determine if two resources belong to the same context or not. In those cases, prefer distinct contexts per resource and refactor later if necessary. Otherwise you can easily end up with large contexts of loosely related entities. Also keep in mind that the fact two resources are related does not necessarily mean they belong to the same context, otherwise you would quickly end up with one large context, as the majority of resources in an application are connected to each other. To sum it up: if you are unsure, you should prefer separate modules (contexts).

$ mix phx.gen.context Catalog Category categories \
title:string:unique

You are generating into an existing context.
...
Would you like to proceed? [Yn] y
* creating lib/hello/catalog/category.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210203192325_create_categories.exs
* injecting lib/hello/catalog.ex
* injecting test/hello/catalog_test.exs
* injecting test/support/fixtures/catalog_fixtures.ex

Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

This time around, we used mix phx.gen.context, which is just like mix phx.gen.html, except it doesn't generate the web files for us. Since we already have controllers and templates for managing products, we can integrate the new category features into our existing web form and product show page. We can see we now have a new Category schema alongside our product schema at lib/hello/catalog/category.ex, and Phoenix told us it was injecting new functions in our existing Catalog context for the category functionality. The injected functions will look very familiar to our product functions, with new functions like create_category, list_categories, and so on. Before we migrate up, we need to do a second bit of code generation. Our category schema is great for representing an individual category in the system, but we need to support a many-to-many relationship between products and categories. Fortunately, ecto allows us to do this simply with a join table, so let's generate that now with the ecto.gen.migration command:

$ mix ecto.gen.migration create_product_categories

* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210203192958_create_product_categories.exs

Next, let's open up the new migration file and add the following code to the change function:

defmodule Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateProductCategories do
  use Ecto.Migration

  def change do
    create table(:product_categories, primary_key: false) do
      add :product_id, references(:products, on_delete: :delete_all)
      add :category_id, references(:categories, on_delete: :delete_all)
    end

    create index(:product_categories, [:product_id])
    create unique_index(:product_categories, [:category_id, :product_id])
  end
end

We created a product_categories table and used the primary_key: false option since our join table does not need a primary key. Next we defined our :product_id and :category_id foreign key fields, and passed on_delete: :delete_all to ensure the database prunes our join table records if a linked product or category is deleted. By using a database constraint, we enforce data integrity at the database level, rather than relying on ad-hoc and error-prone application logic.

Next, we created indexes for our foreign keys, one of which is a unique index to ensure a product cannot have duplicate categories. Note that we do not necessarily need single-column index for category_id because it is in the leftmost prefix of multicolumn index, which is enough for the database optimizer. Adding a redundant index, on the other hand, only adds overhead on write.

With our migrations in place, we can migrate up.

$ mix ecto.migrate

18:20:36.489 [info] == Running 20210222231834 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateCategories.change/0 forward

18:20:36.493 [info] create table categories

18:20:36.508 [info] create index categories_title_index

18:20:36.512 [info] == Migrated 20210222231834 in 0.0s

18:20:36.547 [info] == Running 20210222231930 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateProductCategories.change/0 forward

18:20:36.547 [info] create table product_categories

18:20:36.557 [info] create index product_categories_product_id_index

18:20:36.560 [info]  create index product_categories_category_id_product_id_index

18:20:36.562 [info] == Migrated 20210222231930 in 0.0s

Now that we have a Catalog.Product schema and a join table to associate products and categories, we're nearly ready to start wiring up our new features. Before we dive in, we first need real categories to select in our web UI. Let's quickly seed some new categories in the application. Add the following code to your seeds file in priv/repo/seeds.exs:

for title <- ["Home Improvement", "Power Tools", "Gardening", "Books", "Education"] do
  {:ok, _} = Hello.Catalog.create_category(%{title: title})
end

We simply enumerate over a list of category titles and use the generated create_category/1 function of our catalog context to persist the new records. We can run the seeds with mix run:

$ mix run priv/repo/seeds.exs

[debug] QUERY OK db=3.1ms decode=1.1ms queue=0.7ms idle=2.2ms
INSERT INTO "categories" ("title","inserted_at","updated_at") VALUES ($1,$2,$3) RETURNING "id" ["Home Improvement", ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53], ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53]]
[debug] QUERY OK db=1.2ms queue=1.3ms idle=12.3ms
INSERT INTO "categories" ("title","inserted_at","updated_at") VALUES ($1,$2,$3) RETURNING "id" ["Power Tools", ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53], ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53]]
[debug] QUERY OK db=1.1ms queue=1.1ms idle=15.1ms
INSERT INTO "categories" ("title","inserted_at","updated_at") VALUES ($1,$2,$3) RETURNING "id" ["Gardening", ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53], ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53]]
[debug] QUERY OK db=2.4ms queue=1.0ms idle=17.6ms
INSERT INTO "categories" ("title","inserted_at","updated_at") VALUES ($1,$2,$3) RETURNING "id" ["Books", ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53], ~N[2021-02-03 19:39:53]]

Perfect. Before we integrate categories in the web layer, we need to let our context know how to associate products and categories. First, open up lib/hello/catalog/product.ex and add the following association:

+ alias Hello.Catalog.Category

  schema "products" do
    field :description, :string
    field :price, :decimal
    field :title, :string
    field :views, :integer

+   many_to_many :categories, Category, join_through: "product_categories", on_replace: :delete

    timestamps()
  end

We used Ecto.Schema's many_to_many macro to let Ecto know how to associate our product to multiple categories through the "product_categories" join table. We also used the on_replace: :delete option to declare that any existing join records should be deleted when we are changing our categories.

With our schema associations set up, we can implement the selection of categories in our product form. To do so, we need to translate the user input of catalog IDs from the front-end to our many-to-many association. Fortunately Ecto makes this a breeze now that our schema is set up. Open up your catalog context and make the following changes:

+ alias Hello.Catalog.Category

- def get_product!(id), do: Repo.get!(Product, id)
+ def get_product!(id) do
+   Product |> Repo.get!(id) |> Repo.preload(:categories)
+ end

  def create_product(attrs \\ %{}) do
    %Product{}
-   |> Product.changeset(attrs)
+   |> change_product(attrs)
    |> Repo.insert()
  end

  def update_product(%Product{} = product, attrs) do
    product
-   |> Product.changeset(attrs)
+   |> change_product(attrs)
    |> Repo.update()
  end

  def change_product(%Product{} = product, attrs \\ %{}) do
-   Product.changeset(product, attrs)
+   categories = list_categories_by_id(attrs["category_ids"])

+   product
+   |> Repo.preload(:categories)
+   |> Product.changeset(attrs)
+   |> Ecto.Changeset.put_assoc(:categories, categories)
  end

+ def list_categories_by_id(nil), do: []
+ def list_categories_by_id(category_ids) do
+   Repo.all(from c in Category, where: c.id in ^category_ids)
+ end

First, we added Repo.preload to preload our categories when we fetch a product. This will allow us to reference product.categories in our controllers, templates, and anywhere else we want to make use of category information. Next, we modified our create_product and update_product functions to call into our existing change_product function to produce a changeset. Within change_product we added a lookup to find all categories if the "category_ids" attribute is present. Then we preloaded categories and called Ecto.Changeset.put_assoc to place the fetched categories into the changeset. Finally, we implemented the list_categories_by_id/1 function to query the categories matching the category IDs, or return an empty list if no "category_ids" attribute is present. Now our create_product and update_product functions receive a changeset with the category associations all ready to go once we attempt an insert or update against our repo.

Next, let's expose our new feature to the web by adding the category input to our product form. To keep our form template tidy, let's write a new function to wrap up the details of rendering a category select input for our product. Open up your ProductHTML view in lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html.ex and key this in:

  def category_opts(changeset) do
    existing_ids =
      changeset
      |> Ecto.Changeset.get_change(:categories, [])
      |> Enum.map(& &1.data.id)

    for cat <- Hello.Catalog.list_categories(),
        do: [key: cat.title, value: cat.id, selected: cat.id in existing_ids]
  end

We added a new category_opts/1 function which generates the select options for a multiple select tag we will add soon. We calculated the existing category IDs from our changeset, then used those values when we generate the select options for the input tag. We did this by enumerating over all of our categories and returning the appropriate key, value, and selected values. We marked an option as selected if the category ID was found in those category IDs in our changeset.

With our category_opts function in place, we can open up lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/product_form.html.heex and add:

  ...
  <.input field={f[:views]} type="number" label="Views" />

+ <.input field={f[:category_ids]} type="select" multiple={true} options={category_opts(@changeset)} />

  <:actions>
    <.button>Save Product</.button>
  </:actions>

We added a category_select above our save button. Now let's try it out. Next, let's show the product's categories in the product show template. Add the following code to the list in lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/show.html.heex:

<.list>
  ...
+ <:item title="Categories">
+   <ul>
+     <li :for={cat <- @product.categories}>{cat.title}</li>
+   </ul>
+ </:item>
</.list>

Now if we start the server with mix phx.server and visit http://localhost:4000/products/new, we'll see the new category multiple select input. Enter some valid product details, select a category or two, and click save.

Title: Elixir Flashcards
Description: Flash card set for the Elixir programming language
Price: 5.000000
Views: 0
Categories:
Education
Books

It's not much to look at yet, but it works! We added relationships within our context complete with data integrity enforced by the database. Not bad. Let's keep building!

Cross-context dependencies

Now that we have the beginnings of our product catalog features, let's begin to work on the other main features of our application – carting products from the catalog. In order to properly track products that have been added to a user's cart, we'll need a new place to persist this information, along with point-in-time product information like the price at time of carting. This is necessary so we can detect product price changes in the future. We know what we need to build, but now we need to decide where the cart functionality lives in our application.

If we take a step back and think about the isolation of our application, the exhibition of products in our catalog distinctly differs from the responsibilities of managing a user's cart. A product catalog shouldn't care about the rules of our shopping cart system, and vice-versa. There's a clear need here for a separate context to handle the new cart responsibilities. Let's call it ShoppingCart.

Let's create a ShoppingCart context to handle basic cart duties. Before we write code, let's imagine we have the following feature requirements:

Add products to a user's cart from the product show page
Store point-in-time product price information at time of carting
Store and update quantities in cart
Calculate and display sum of cart prices

From the description, it's clear we need a Cart resource for storing the user's cart, along with a CartItem to track products in the cart. With our plan set, let's get to work. Run the following command to generate our new context:

$ mix phx.gen.context ShoppingCart Cart carts user_uuid:uuid:unique

* creating lib/hello/shopping_cart/cart.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210205203128_create_carts.exs
* creating lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex
* injecting lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex
* creating test/hello/shopping_cart_test.exs
* injecting test/hello/shopping_cart_test.exs
* creating test/support/fixtures/shopping_cart_fixtures.ex
* injecting test/support/fixtures/shopping_cart_fixtures.ex

Some of the generated database columns are unique. Please provide
unique implementations for the following fixture function(s) in
test/support/fixtures/shopping_cart_fixtures.ex:

    def unique_cart_user_uuid do
      raise "implement the logic to generate a unique cart user_uuid"
    end

Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

We generated our new context ShoppingCart, with a new ShoppingCart.Cart schema to tie a user to their cart which holds cart items. We don't have real users yet, so for now our cart will be tracked by an anonymous user UUID that we'll add to our plug session in a moment. With our cart in place, let's generate our cart items:

$ mix phx.gen.context ShoppingCart CartItem cart_items \
cart_id:references:carts product_id:references:products \
price_when_carted:decimal quantity:integer

You are generating into an existing context.
...
Would you like to proceed? [Yn] y
* creating lib/hello/shopping_cart/cart_item.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210205213410_create_cart_items.exs
* injecting lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex
* injecting test/hello/shopping_cart_test.exs
* injecting test/support/fixtures/shopping_cart_fixtures.ex

Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

We generated a new resource inside our ShoppingCart named CartItem. This schema and table will hold references to a cart and product, along with the price at the time we added the item to our cart, and the quantity the user wishes to purchase. Let's touch up the generated migration file in priv/repo/migrations/*_create_cart_items.ex:

    create table(:cart_items) do
-     add :price_when_carted, :decimal
+     add :price_when_carted, :decimal, precision: 15, scale: 6, null: false
      add :quantity, :integer
-     add :cart_id, references(:carts, on_delete: :nothing)
+     add :cart_id, references(:carts, on_delete: :delete_all)
-     add :product_id, references(:products, on_delete: :nothing)
+     add :product_id, references(:products, on_delete: :delete_all)

      timestamps()
    end

-   create index(:cart_items, [:cart_id])
    create index(:cart_items, [:product_id])
+   create unique_index(:cart_items, [:cart_id, :product_id])

We used the :delete_all strategy again to enforce data integrity. This way, when a cart or product is deleted from the application, we don't have to rely on application code in our ShoppingCart or Catalog contexts to worry about cleaning up the records. This keeps our application code decoupled and the data integrity enforcement where it belongs – in the database. We also added a unique constraint to ensure a duplicate product is not allowed to be added to a cart. As with the product_categories table, using a multi-column index lets us remove the separate index for the leftmost field (cart_id). With our database tables in place, we can now migrate up:

$ mix ecto.migrate

16:59:51.941 [info] == Running 20210205203342 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateCarts.change/0 forward

16:59:51.945 [info] create table carts

16:59:51.949 [info] create index carts_user_uuid_index

16:59:51.952 [info] == Migrated 20210205203342 in 0.0s

16:59:51.988 [info] == Running 20210205213410 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateCartItems.change/0 forward

16:59:51.988 [info] create table cart_items

16:59:51.998 [info] create index cart_items_cart_id_index

16:59:52.000 [info] create index cart_items_product_id_index

16:59:52.001 [info] create index cart_items_cart_id_product_id_index

16:59:52.002 [info] == Migrated 20210205213410 in 0.0s

Our database is ready to go with new carts and cart_items tables, but now we need to map that back into application code. You may be wondering how we can mix database foreign keys across different tables and how that relates to the context pattern of isolated, grouped functionality. Let's jump in and discuss the approaches and their tradeoffs.

Cross-context data

So far, we've done a great job isolating the two main contexts of our application from each other, but now we have a necessary dependency to handle.

Our Catalog.Product resource serves to keep the responsibilities of representing a product inside the catalog, but ultimately for an item to exist in the cart, a product from the catalog must be present. Given this, our ShoppingCart context will have a data dependency on the Catalog context. With that in mind, we have two options. One is to expose APIs on the Catalog context that allows us to efficiently fetch product data for use in the ShoppingCart system, which we would manually stitch together. Or we can use database joins to fetch the dependent data. Both are valid options given your tradeoffs and application size, but joining data from the database when you have a hard data dependency is just fine for a large class of applications and is the approach we will take here.

Now that we know where our data dependencies exist, let's add our schema associations so we can tie shopping cart items to products. First, let's make a quick change to our cart schema in lib/hello/shopping_cart/cart.ex to associate a cart to its items:

  schema "carts" do
    field :user_uuid, Ecto.UUID

+   has_many :items, Hello.ShoppingCart.CartItem

    timestamps()
  end

Now that our cart is associated to the items we place in it, let's set up the cart item associations inside lib/hello/shopping_cart/cart_item.ex:

  schema "cart_items" do
    field :price_when_carted, :decimal
    field :quantity, :integer
-   field :cart_id, :id
-   field :product_id, :id

+   belongs_to :cart, Hello.ShoppingCart.Cart
+   belongs_to :product, Hello.Catalog.Product

    timestamps()
  end

  @doc false
  def changeset(cart_item, attrs) do
    cart_item
    |> cast(attrs, [:price_when_carted, :quantity])
    |> validate_required([:price_when_carted, :quantity])
+   |> validate_number(:quantity, greater_than_or_equal_to: 0, less_than: 100)
  end

First, we replaced the cart_id field with a standard belongs_to pointing at our ShoppingCart.Cart schema. Next, we replaced our product_id field by adding our first cross-context data dependency with a belongs_to for the Catalog.Product schema. Here, we intentionally coupled the data boundaries because it provides exactly what we need: an isolated context API with the bare minimum knowledge necessary to reference a product in our system. Next, we added a new validation to our changeset. With validate_number/3, we ensure any quantity provided by user input is between 0 and 100.

With our schemas in place, we can start integrating the new data structures and ShoppingCart context APIs into our web-facing features.

Adding Shopping Cart functions

As we mentioned before, the context generators are only a starting point for our application. We can and should write well-named, purpose built functions to accomplish the goals of our context. We have a few new features to implement. First, we need to ensure every user of our application is granted a cart if one does not yet exist. From there, we can then allow users to add items to their cart, update item quantities, and calculate cart totals. Let's get started!

We won't focus on a real user authentication system at this point, but by the time we're done, you'll be able to naturally integrate one with what we've written here. To simulate a current user session, open up your lib/hello_web/router.ex and key this in:

  pipeline :browser do
    plug :accepts, ["html"]
    plug :fetch_session
    plug :fetch_live_flash
    plug :put_root_layout, html: {HelloWeb.LayoutView, :root}
    plug :protect_from_forgery
    plug :put_secure_browser_headers
+   plug :fetch_current_user
+   plug :fetch_current_cart
  end

+ defp fetch_current_user(conn, _) do
+   if user_uuid = get_session(conn, :current_uuid) do
+     assign(conn, :current_uuid, user_uuid)
+   else
+     new_uuid = Ecto.UUID.generate()
+
+     conn
+     |> assign(:current_uuid, new_uuid)
+     |> put_session(:current_uuid, new_uuid)
+   end
+ end

+ alias Hello.ShoppingCart
+
+ defp fetch_current_cart(conn, _opts) do
+   if cart = ShoppingCart.get_cart_by_user_uuid(conn.assigns.current_uuid) do
+     assign(conn, :cart, cart)
+   else
+     {:ok, new_cart} = ShoppingCart.create_cart(conn.assigns.current_uuid)
+     assign(conn, :cart, new_cart)
+   end
+ end

We added a new :fetch_current_user and :fetch_current_cart plug to our browser pipeline to run on all browser-based requests. Next, we implemented the fetch_current_user plug which simply checks the session for a user UUID that was previously added. If we find one, we add a current_uuid assign to the connection and we're done. In the case we haven't yet identified this visitor, we generate a unique UUID with Ecto.UUID.generate(), then we place that value in the current_uuid assign, along with a new session value to identify this visitor on future requests. A random, unique ID isn't much to represent a user, but it's enough for us to track and identify a visitor across requests, which is all we need for now. Later as our application becomes more complete, you'll be ready to migrate to a complete user authentication solution. With a guaranteed current user, we then implemented the fetch_current_cart plug which either finds a cart for the user UUID or creates a cart for the current user and assigns the result in the connection assigns. We'll need to implement our ShoppingCart.get_cart_by_user_uuid/1 and modify the create cart function to accept a UUID, but let's add our routes first.

We'll need to implement a cart controller for handling cart operations like viewing a cart, updating quantities, and initiating the checkout process, as well as a cart items controller for adding and removing individual items to and from the cart. Add the following routes to your router in lib/hello_web/router.ex:

  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    get "/", PageController, :index
    resources "/products", ProductController

+   resources "/cart_items", CartItemController, only: [:create, :delete]

+   get "/cart", CartController, :show
+   put "/cart", CartController, :update
  end

We added a resources declaration for a CartItemController, which will wire up the routes for a create and delete action for adding and removing individual cart items. Next, we added two new routes pointing at a CartController. The first route, a GET request, will map to our show action, to show the cart contents. The second route, a PUT request, will handle the submission of a form for updating our cart quantities.

With our routes in place, let's add the ability to add an item to our cart from the product show page. Create a new file at lib/hello_web/controllers/cart_item_controller.ex and key this in:

defmodule HelloWeb.CartItemController do
  use HelloWeb, :controller

  alias Hello.ShoppingCart

  def create(conn, %{"product_id" => product_id}) do
    case ShoppingCart.add_item_to_cart(conn.assigns.cart, product_id) do
      {:ok, _item} ->
        conn
        |> put_flash(:info, "Item added to your cart")
        |> redirect(to: ~p"/cart")

      {:error, _changeset} ->
        conn
        |> put_flash(:error, "There was an error adding the item to your cart")
        |> redirect(to: ~p"/cart")
    end
  end

  def delete(conn, %{"id" => product_id}) do
    {:ok, _cart} = ShoppingCart.remove_item_from_cart(conn.assigns.cart, product_id)
    redirect(conn, to: ~p"/cart")
  end
end

We defined a new CartItemController with the create and delete actions that we declared in our router. For create, we call a ShoppingCart.add_item_to_cart/2 function which we'll implement in a moment. If successful, we show a flash successful message and redirect to the cart show page; else, we show a flash error message and redirect to the cart show page. For delete, we'll call a remove_item_from_cart function which we'll implement on our ShoppingCart context and then redirect back to the cart show page. We haven't implemented these two shopping cart functions yet, but notice how their names scream their intent: add_item_to_cart and remove_item_from_cart make it obvious what we are accomplishing here. It also allows us to spec out our web layer and context APIs without thinking about all the implementation details at once.

Let's implement the new interface for the ShoppingCart context API in lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex:

+  alias Hello.Catalog
-  alias Hello.ShoppingCart.Cart
+  alias Hello.ShoppingCart.{Cart, CartItem}

+  def get_cart_by_user_uuid(user_uuid) do
+    Repo.one(
+      from(c in Cart,
+        where: c.user_uuid == ^user_uuid,
+        left_join: i in assoc(c, :items),
+        left_join: p in assoc(i, :product),
+        order_by: [asc: i.inserted_at],
+        preload: [items: {i, product: p}]
+      )
+    )
+  end

- def create_cart(attrs \\ %{}) do
-   %Cart{}
-   |> Cart.changeset(attrs)
+ def create_cart(user_uuid) do
+   %Cart{user_uuid: user_uuid}
+   |> Cart.changeset(%{})
    |> Repo.insert()
+   |> case do
+     {:ok, cart} -> {:ok, reload_cart(cart)}
+     {:error, changeset} -> {:error, changeset}
+   end
  end

+  defp reload_cart(%Cart{} = cart), do: get_cart_by_user_uuid(cart.user_uuid)
+
+  def add_item_to_cart(%Cart{} = cart, product_id) do
+    product = Catalog.get_product!(product_id)
+
+    %CartItem{quantity: 1, price_when_carted: product.price}
+    |> CartItem.changeset(%{})
+    |> Ecto.Changeset.put_assoc(:cart, cart)
+    |> Ecto.Changeset.put_assoc(:product, product)
+    |> Repo.insert(
+      on_conflict: [inc: [quantity: 1]],
+      conflict_target: [:cart_id, :product_id]
+    )
+  end
+
+  def remove_item_from_cart(%Cart{} = cart, product_id) do
+    {1, _} =
+      Repo.delete_all(
+        from(i in CartItem,
+          where: i.cart_id == ^cart.id,
+          where: i.product_id == ^product_id
+        )
+      )
+
+    {:ok, reload_cart(cart)}
+  end

We started by implementing get_cart_by_user_uuid/1 which fetches our cart and joins the cart items, and their products so that we have the full cart populated with all preloaded data. Next, we modified our create_cart function to accept a user UUID instead of attributes, which we used to populate the user_uuid field. If the insert is successful, we reload the cart contents by calling a private reload_cart/1 function, which simply calls get_cart_by_user_uuid/1 to refetch data.

Next, we wrote our new add_item_to_cart/2 function which accepts a cart struct and a product id. We proceed to fetch the product with Catalog.get_product!/1, showing how contexts can naturally invoke other contexts if required. You could also have chosen to receive the product as argument and you would achieve similar results. Then we used an upsert operation against our repo to either insert a new cart item into the database, or increase the quantity by one if it already exists in the cart. This is accomplished via the on_conflict and conflict_target options, which tells our repo how to handle an insert conflict.

Finally, we implemented remove_item_from_cart/2 where we simply issue a Repo.delete_all call with a query to delete the cart item in our cart that matches the product ID. Finally, we reload the cart contents by calling reload_cart/1.

With our new cart functions in place, we can now expose the "Add to cart" button on the product catalog show page. Open up your template in lib/hello_web/controllers/product_html/show.html.heex and make the following changes:

...
     <.link href={~p"/products/#{@product}/edit"}>
       <.button>Edit product</.button>
     </.link>
+    <.link href={~p"/cart_items?product_id=#{@product.id}"} method="post">
+      <.button>Add to cart</.button>
+    </.link>
...

The link function component from Phoenix.Component accepts a :method attribute to issue an HTTP verb when clicked, instead of the default GET request. With this link in place, the "Add to cart" link will issue a POST request, which will be matched by the route we defined in router which dispatches to the CartItemController.create/2 function.

Let's try it out. Start your server with mix phx.server and visit a product page. If we try clicking the add to cart link, we'll be greeted by an error page with the following logs in the console:

[info] POST /cart_items
[debug] Processing with HelloWeb.CartItemController.create/2
  Parameters: %{"_method" => "post", "product_id" => "1", ...}
  Pipelines: [:browser]
INSERT INTO "cart_items" ...
[info] Sent 302 in 24ms
[info] GET /cart
[debug] Processing with HelloWeb.CartController.show/2
  Parameters: %{}
  Pipelines: [:browser]
[debug] QUERY OK source="carts" db=1.9ms idle=1798.5ms

[error] #PID<0.856.0> running HelloWeb.Endpoint (connection #PID<0.841.0>, stream id 5) terminated
Server: localhost:4000 (http)
Request: GET /cart
** (exit) an exception was raised:
    ** (UndefinedFunctionError) function HelloWeb.CartController.init/1 is undefined
       (module HelloWeb.CartController is not available)
       ...

It's working! Kind of. If we follow the logs, we see our POST to the /cart_items path. Next, we can see our ShoppingCart.add_item_to_cart function successfully inserted a row into the cart_items table, and then we issued a redirect to /cart. Before our error, we also see a query to the carts table, which means we're fetching the current user's cart. So far so good. We know our CartItem controller and new ShoppingCart context functions are doing their jobs, but we've hit our next unimplemented feature when the router attempts to dispatch to a nonexistent cart controller. Let's create the cart controller, view, and template to display and manage user carts.

Create a new file at lib/hello_web/controllers/cart_controller.ex and key this in:

defmodule HelloWeb.CartController do
  use HelloWeb, :controller

  alias Hello.ShoppingCart

  def show(conn, _params) do
    render(conn, :show, changeset: ShoppingCart.change_cart(conn.assigns.cart))
  end
end

We defined a new cart controller to handle the get "/cart" route. For showing a cart, we render a "show.html" template which we'll create in a moment. We know we need to allow the cart items to be changed by quantity updates, so right away we know we'll need a cart changeset. Fortunately, the context generator included a ShoppingCart.change_cart/1 function, which we'll use. We pass it our cart struct which is already in the connection assigns thanks to the fetch_current_cart plug we defined in the router.

Next, we can implement the view and template. Create a new view file at lib/hello_web/controllers/cart_html.ex with the following content:

defmodule HelloWeb.CartHTML do
  use HelloWeb, :html

  alias Hello.ShoppingCart

  embed_templates "cart_html/*"

  def currency_to_str(%Decimal{} = val), do: "$#{Decimal.round(val, 2)}"
end

We created a view to render our show.html template and aliased our ShoppingCart context so it will be in scope for our template. We'll need to display the cart prices like product item price, cart total, etc, so we defined a currency_to_str/1 which takes our decimal struct, rounds it properly for display, and prepends a USD dollar sign.

Next we can create the template at lib/hello_web/controllers/cart_html/show.html.heex:

<.header>
  My Cart
  <:subtitle :if={@cart.items == []}>Your cart is empty</:subtitle>
</.header>

<div :if={@cart.items !== []}>
  <.simple_form :let={f} for={@changeset} action={~p"/cart"}>
    <.inputs_for :let={%{data: item} = item_form} field={f[:items]}>
      <.input field={item_form[:quantity]} type="number" label={item.product.title} />
      {currency_to_str(ShoppingCart.total_item_price(item))}
    </.inputs_for>
    <:actions>
      <.button>Update cart</.button>
    </:actions>
  </.simple_form>
  <b>Total</b>: {currency_to_str(ShoppingCart.total_cart_price(@cart))}
</div>

<.back navigate={~p"/products"}>Back to products</.back>

We started by showing the empty cart message if our preloaded cart.items is empty. If we have items, we use the simple_form component provided by our HelloWeb.CoreComponents to take our cart changeset that we assigned in the CartController.show/2 action and create a form which maps to our cart controller update/2 action. Within the form, we use the inputs_for component to render inputs for the nested cart items. This will allow us to map item inputs back together when the form is submitted. Next, we display a number input for the item quantity and label it with the product title. We finish the item form by converting the item price to string. We haven't written the ShoppingCart.total_item_price/1 function yet, but again we employed the idea of clear, descriptive public interfaces for our contexts. After rendering inputs for all the cart items, we show an "update cart" submit button, along with the total price of the entire cart. This is accomplished with another new ShoppingCart.total_cart_price/1 function which we'll implement in a moment. Finally, we added a back component to go back to our products page.

We're almost ready to try out our cart page, but first we need to implement our new currency calculation functions. Open up your shopping cart context at lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex and add these new functions:

  def total_item_price(%CartItem{} = item) do
    Decimal.mult(item.product.price, item.quantity)
  end

  def total_cart_price(%Cart{} = cart) do
    Enum.reduce(cart.items, 0, fn item, acc ->
      item
      |> total_item_price()
      |> Decimal.add(acc)
    end)
  end

We implemented total_item_price/1 which accepts a %CartItem{} struct. To calculate the total price, we simply take the preloaded product's price and multiply it by the item's quantity. We used Decimal.mult/2 to take our decimal currency struct and multiply it with proper precision. Similarly for calculating the total cart price, we implemented a total_cart_price/1 function which accepts the cart and sums the preloaded product prices for items in the cart. We again make use of the Decimal functions to add our decimal structs together.

Now that we can calculate price totals, let's try it out! Visit http://localhost:4000/cart and you should already see your first item in the cart. Going back to the same product and clicking "add to cart" will show our upsert in action. Your quantity should now be two. Nice work!

Our cart page is almost complete, but submitting the form will yield yet another error.

Request: POST /cart
** (exit) an exception was raised:
    ** (UndefinedFunctionError) function HelloWeb.CartController.update/2 is undefined or private

Let's head back to our CartController at lib/hello_web/controllers/cart_controller.ex and implement the update action:

  def update(conn, %{"cart" => cart_params}) do
    case ShoppingCart.update_cart(conn.assigns.cart, cart_params) do
      {:ok, _cart} ->
        redirect(conn, to: ~p"/cart")

      {:error, _changeset} ->
        conn
        |> put_flash(:error, "There was an error updating your cart")
        |> redirect(to: ~p"/cart")
    end
  end

We started by plucking out the cart params from the form submit. Next, we call our existing ShoppingCart.update_cart/2 function which was added by the context generator. We'll need to make some changes to this function, but the interface is good as is. If the update is successful, we redirect back to the cart page, otherwise we show a flash error message and send the user back to the cart page to fix any mistakes. Out-of-the-box, our ShoppingCart.update_cart/2 function only concerned itself with casting the cart params into a changeset and updates it against our repo. For our purposes, we now need it to handle nested cart item associations, and most importantly, business logic for how to handle quantity updates like zero-quantity items being removed from the cart.

Head back over to your shopping cart context in lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex and replace your update_cart/2 function with the following implementation:

  def update_cart(%Cart{} = cart, attrs) do
    changeset =
      cart
      |> Cart.changeset(attrs)
      |> Ecto.Changeset.cast_assoc(:items, with: &CartItem.changeset/2)

    Ecto.Multi.new()
    |> Ecto.Multi.update(:cart, changeset)
    |> Ecto.Multi.delete_all(:discarded_items, fn %{cart: cart} ->
      from(i in CartItem, where: i.cart_id == ^cart.id and i.quantity == 0)
    end)
    |> Repo.transaction()
    |> case do
      {:ok, %{cart: cart}} -> {:ok, cart}
      {:error, :cart, changeset, _changes_so_far} -> {:error, changeset}
    end
  end

We started much like how our out-of-the-box code started – we take the cart struct and cast the user input to a cart changeset, except this time we use Ecto.Changeset.cast_assoc/3 to cast the nested item data into CartItem changesets. Remember the <.inputs_for /> call in our cart form template? That hidden ID data is what allows Ecto's cast_assoc to map item data back to existing item associations in the cart. Next we use Ecto.Multi.new/0, which you may not have seen before. Ecto's Multi is a feature that allows lazily defining a chain of named operations to eventually execute inside a database transaction. Each operation in the multi chain receives the values from the previous steps and executes until a failed step is encountered. When an operation fails, the transaction is rolled back and an error is returned, otherwise the transaction is committed.

For our multi operations, we start by issuing an update of our cart, which we named :cart. After the cart update is issued, we perform a multi delete_all operation, which takes the updated cart and applies our zero-quantity logic. We prune any items in the cart with zero quantity by returning an ecto query that finds all cart items for this cart with an empty quantity. Calling Repo.transaction/1 with our multi will execute the operations in a new transaction and we return the success or failure result to the caller just like the original function.

Let's head back to the browser and try it out. Add a few products to your cart, update the quantities, and watch the values changes along with the price calculations. Setting any quantity to 0 will also remove the item. Pretty neat!

Adding an Orders context

With our Catalog and ShoppingCart contexts, we're seeing first-hand how our well-considered modules and function names are yielding clear and maintainable code. Our last order of business is to allow the user to initiate the checkout process. We won't go as far as integrating payment processing or order fulfillment, but we'll get you started in that direction. Like before, we need to decide where code for completing an order should live. Is it part of the catalog? Clearly not, but what about the shopping cart? Shopping carts are related to orders – after all, the user has to add items in order to purchase any products – but should the order checkout process be grouped here?

If we stop and consider the order process, we'll see that orders involve related, but distinctly different data from the cart contents. Also, business rules around the checkout process are much different than carting. For example, we may allow a user to add a back-ordered item to their cart, but we could not allow an order with no inventory to be completed. Additionally, we need to capture point-in-time product information when an order is completed, such as the price of the items at payment transaction time. This is essential because a product price may change in the future, but the line items in our order must always record and display what we charged at time of purchase. For these reasons, we can start to see that ordering can stand on its own with its own data concerns and business rules.

Naming wise, Orders clearly defines the scope of our context, so let's get started by again taking advantage of the context generators. Run the following command in your console:

$ mix phx.gen.context Orders Order orders user_uuid:uuid total_price:decimal

* creating lib/hello/orders/order.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210209214612_create_orders.exs
* creating lib/hello/orders.ex
* injecting lib/hello/orders.ex
* creating test/hello/orders_test.exs
* injecting test/hello/orders_test.exs
* creating test/support/fixtures/orders_fixtures.ex
* injecting test/support/fixtures/orders_fixtures.ex

Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

We generated an Orders context. We added a user_uuid field to associate our placeholder current user to an order, along with a total_price column. With our starting point in place, let's open up the newly created migration in priv/repo/migrations/*_create_orders.exs and make the following changes:

  def change do
    create table(:orders) do
      add :user_uuid, :uuid
-     add :total_price, :decimal
+     add :total_price, :decimal, precision: 15, scale: 6, null: false

      timestamps()
    end
  end

Like we did previously, we gave appropriate precision and scale options for our decimal column which will allow us to store currency without precision loss. We also added a not-null constraint to enforce all orders to have a price.

The orders table alone doesn't hold much information, but we know we'll need to store point-in-time product price information of all the items in the order. For that, we'll add an additional struct for this context named LineItem. Line items will capture the price of the product at payment transaction time. Please run the following command:

$ mix phx.gen.context Orders LineItem order_line_items \
price:decimal quantity:integer \
order_id:references:orders product_id:references:products

You are generating into an existing context.
...
Would you like to proceed? [Yn] y
* creating lib/hello/orders/line_item.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20210209215050_create_order_line_items.exs
* injecting lib/hello/orders.ex
* injecting test/hello/orders_test.exs
* injecting test/support/fixtures/orders_fixtures.ex

Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

We used the phx.gen.context command to generate the LineItem Ecto schema and inject supporting functions into our orders context. Like before, let's modify the migration in priv/repo/migrations/*_create_order_line_items.exs and make the following decimal field changes:

  def change do
    create table(:order_line_items) do
-     add :price, :decimal
+     add :price, :decimal, precision: 15, scale: 6, null: false
      add :quantity, :integer
      add :order_id, references(:orders, on_delete: :nothing)
      add :product_id, references(:products, on_delete: :nothing)

      timestamps()
    end

    create index(:order_line_items, [:order_id])
    create index(:order_line_items, [:product_id])
  end

With our migration in place, let's wire up our orders and line items associations in lib/hello/orders/order.ex:

  schema "orders" do
    field :total_price, :decimal
    field :user_uuid, Ecto.UUID

+   has_many :line_items, Hello.Orders.LineItem
+   has_many :products, through: [:line_items, :product]

    timestamps()
  end

We used has_many :line_items to associate orders and line items, just like we've seen before. Next, we used the :through feature of has_many, which allows us to instruct ecto how to associate resources across another relationship. In this case, we can associate products of an order by finding all products through associated line items. Next, let's wire up the association in the other direction in lib/hello/orders/line_item.ex:

  schema "order_line_items" do
    field :price, :decimal
    field :quantity, :integer
-   field :order_id, :id
-   field :product_id, :id

+   belongs_to :order, Hello.Orders.Order
+   belongs_to :product, Hello.Catalog.Product

    timestamps()
  end

We used belongs_to to associate line items to orders and products. With our associations in place, we can start integrating the web interface into our order process. Open up your router lib/hello_web/router.ex and add the following line:

  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    ...
+   resources "/orders", OrderController, only: [:create, :show]
  end

We wired up create and show routes for our generated OrderController, since these are the only actions we need at the moment. With our routes in place, we can now migrate up:

$ mix ecto.migrate

17:14:37.715 [info] == Running 20210209214612 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateOrders.change/0 forward

17:14:37.720 [info] create table orders

17:14:37.755 [info] == Migrated 20210209214612 in 0.0s

17:14:37.784 [info] == Running 20210209215050 Hello.Repo.Migrations.CreateOrderLineItems.change/0 forward

17:14:37.785 [info] create table order_line_items

17:14:37.795 [info] create index order_line_items_order_id_index

17:14:37.796 [info] create index order_line_items_product_id_index

17:14:37.798 [info] == Migrated 20210209215050 in 0.0s

Before we render information about our orders, we need to ensure our order data is fully populated and can be looked up by a current user. Open up your orders context in lib/hello/orders.ex and replace your get_order!/1 function by a new get_order!/2 definition:

  def get_order!(user_uuid, id) do
    Order
    |> Repo.get_by!(id: id, user_uuid: user_uuid)
    |> Repo.preload([line_items: [:product]])
  end

We rewrote the function to accept a user UUID and query our repo for an order matching the user's ID for a given order ID. Then we populated the order by preloading our line item and product associations.

To complete an order, our cart page can issue a POST to the OrderController.create action, but we need to implement the operations and logic to actually complete an order. Like before, we'll start at the web interface. Create a new file at lib/hello_web/controllers/order_controller.ex and key this in:

defmodule HelloWeb.OrderController do
  use HelloWeb, :controller

  alias Hello.Orders

  def create(conn, _) do
    case Orders.complete_order(conn.assigns.cart) do
      {:ok, order} ->
        conn
        |> put_flash(:info, "Order created successfully.")
        |> redirect(to: ~p"/orders/#{order}")

      {:error, _reason} ->
        conn
        |> put_flash(:error, "There was an error processing your order")
        |> redirect(to: ~p"/cart")
    end
  end
end

We wrote the create action to call an as-yet-implemented Orders.complete_order/1 function. Our code is technically "creating" an order, but it's important to step back and consider the naming of your interfaces. The act of completing an order is extremely important in our system. Money changes hands in a transaction, physical goods could be automatically shipped, etc. Such an operation deserves a better, more obvious function name, such as complete_order. If the order is completed successfully we redirect to the show page, otherwise a flash error is shown as we redirect back to the cart page.

Here is also a good opportunity to highlight that contexts can naturally work with data defined by other contexts too. This will be especially common with data that is used throughout the application, such as the cart here (but it can also be the current user or the current project, and so forth, depending on your project).

Now we can implement our Orders.complete_order/1 function. To complete an order, our job will require a few operations:

A new order record must be persisted with the total price of the order
All items in the cart must be transformed into new order line items records with quantity and point-in-time product price information
After successful order insert (and eventual payment), items must be pruned from the cart

From our requirements alone, we can start to see why a generic create_order function doesn't cut it. Let's implement this new function in lib/hello/orders.ex:

  alias Hello.Orders.LineItem
  alias Hello.ShoppingCart

  def complete_order(%ShoppingCart.Cart{} = cart) do
    line_items =
      Enum.map(cart.items, fn item ->
        %{product_id: item.product_id, price: item.product.price, quantity: item.quantity}
      end)

    order =
      Ecto.Changeset.change(%Order{},
        user_uuid: cart.user_uuid,
        total_price: ShoppingCart.total_cart_price(cart),
        line_items: line_items
      )

    Ecto.Multi.new()
    |> Ecto.Multi.insert(:order, order)
    |> Ecto.Multi.run(:prune_cart, fn _repo, _changes ->
      ShoppingCart.prune_cart_items(cart)
    end)
    |> Repo.transaction()
    |> case do
      {:ok, %{order: order}} -> {:ok, order}
      {:error, name, value, _changes_so_far} -> {:error, {name, value}}
    end
  end

We started by mapping the %ShoppingCart.CartItem{}'s in our shopping cart into a map of order line items structs. The job of the order line item record is to capture the price of the product at payment transaction time, so we reference the product's price here. Next, we create a bare order changeset with Ecto.Changeset.change/2 and associate our user UUID, set our total price calculation, and place our order line items in the changeset. With a fresh order changeset ready to be inserted, we can again make use of Ecto.Multi to execute our operations in a database transaction. We start by inserting the order, followed by a run operation. The Ecto.Multi.run/3 function allows us to run any code in the function which must either succeed with {:ok, result} or error, which halts and rolls back the transaction. Here, we simply call into our shopping cart context and ask it to prune all items in a cart. Running the transaction will execute the multi as before and we return the result to the caller.

To close out our order completion, we need to implement the ShoppingCart.prune_cart_items/1 function in lib/hello/shopping_cart.ex:

  def prune_cart_items(%Cart{} = cart) do
    {_, _} = Repo.delete_all(from(i in CartItem, where: i.cart_id == ^cart.id))
    {:ok, reload_cart(cart)}
  end

Our new function accepts the cart struct and issues a Repo.delete_all which accepts a query of all items for the provided cart. We return a success result by simply reloading the pruned cart to the caller. With our context complete, we now need to show the user their completed order. Head back to your order controller and add the show/2 action:

  def show(conn, %{"id" => id}) do
    order = Orders.get_order!(conn.assigns.current_uuid, id)
    render(conn, :show, order: order)
  end

We added the show action to pass our conn.assigns.current_uuid to get_order! which authorizes orders to be viewable only by the owner of the order. Next, we can implement the view and template. Create a new view file at lib/hello_web/controllers/order_html.ex with the following content:

defmodule HelloWeb.OrderHTML do
  use HelloWeb, :html

  embed_templates "order_html/*"
end

Next we can create the template at lib/hello_web/controllers/order_html/show.html.heex:

<.header>
  Thank you for your order!
  <:subtitle>
     <strong>User uuid: </strong>{@order.user_uuid}
  </:subtitle>
</.header>

<.table id="items" rows={@order.line_items}>
  <:col :let={item} label="Title">{item.product.title}</:col>
  <:col :let={item} label="Quantity">{item.quantity}</:col>
  <:col :let={item} label="Price">
    {HelloWeb.CartHTML.currency_to_str(item.price)}
  </:col>
</.table>

<strong>Total price:</strong>
{HelloWeb.CartHTML.currency_to_str(@order.total_price)}

<.back navigate={~p"/products"}>Back to products</.back>

To show our completed order, we displayed the order's user, followed by the line item listing with product title, quantity, and the price we "transacted" when completing the order, along with the total price.

Our last addition will be to add the "complete order" button to our cart page to allow completing an order. Add the following button to the <.header> of the cart show template in lib/hello_web/controllers/cart_html/show.html.heex:

  <.header>
    My Cart
+   <:actions>
+     <.link href={~p"/orders"} method="post">
+       <.button>Complete order</.button>
+     </.link>
+   </:actions>
  </.header>

We added a link with method="post" to send a POST request to our OrderController.create action. If we head back to our cart page at http://localhost:4000/cart and complete an order, we'll be greeted by our rendered template:

Thank you for your order!

User uuid: 08964c7c-908c-4a55-bcd3-9811ad8b0b9d
Title                   Quantity Price
Metaprogramming Elixir  2        $15.00

Total price: $30.00

Nice work! We haven't added payments, but we can already see how our ShoppingCart and Orders context splitting is driving us towards a maintainable solution. With our cart items separated from our order line items, we are well equipped in the future to add payment transactions, cart price detection, and more.

Great work!

FAQ

When to use code generators?

In this guide, we have used code generators for schemas, contexts, controllers, and more. If you are happy to move forward with Phoenix defaults, feel free to rely on generators to scaffold large parts of your application. When using Phoenix generators, the main question you need to answer is: does this new functionality (with its schema, table, and fields) belong to one of the existing contexts or a new one?

This way, Phoenix generators guide you to use contexts to group related functionality, instead of having several dozens of schemas laying around without any structure. And remember: if you're stuck when trying to come up with a context name, you can simply use the plural form of the resource you're creating.

How do I structure code inside contexts?

You may wonder how to organize the code inside contexts. For example, should you define a module for changesets (such as ProductChangesets) and another module for queries (such as ProductQueries)?

One important benefit of contexts is that this decision does not matter much. The context is your public API, the other modules are private. Contexts isolate these modules into small groups so the surface area of your application is the context and not all of your code.

So while you and your team could establish patterns for organizing these private modules, it is also our opinion it is completely fine for them to be different. The major focus should be on how the contexts are defined and how they interact with each other (and with your web application).

Think about it as a well-kept neighbourhood. Your contexts are houses, you want to keep them well-preserved, well-connected, etc. Inside the houses, they may all be a little bit different, and that's fine.

Returning Ecto structures from context APIs

As we explored the context API, you might have wondered:

If one of the goals of our context is to encapsulate Ecto Repo access, why does create_user/1 return an Ecto.Changeset struct when we fail to create a user?

Although Changesets are part of Ecto, they are not tied to the database, and they can be used to map data from and to any source, which makes it a general and useful data structure for tracking field changes, perform validations, and generate error messages.

For those reasons, %Ecto.Changeset{} is a good choice to model the data changes between your contexts and your web layer - regardless if you are talking to an API or the database.

Finally, note that your controllers and views are not hardcoded to work exclusively with Ecto either. Instead, Phoenix defines protocols such as Phoenix.Param and Phoenix.HTML.FormData, which allow any library to extend how Phoenix generates URL parameters or renders forms. Conveniently for us, the phoenix_ecto project implements those protocols, but you could as well bring your own data structures and implement them yourself.

Introduction to Deployment

Once we have a working application, we're ready to deploy it. If you're not quite finished with your own application, don't worry. Just follow the Up and Running Guide to create a basic application to work with.

When preparing an application for deployment, there are three main steps:

Handling of your application secrets
Compiling your application assets
Starting your server in production

In this guide, we will learn how to get the production environment running locally. You can use the same techniques in this guide to run your application in production, but depending on your deployment infrastructure, extra steps will be necessary.

As an example of deploying to other infrastructures, we also discuss four different approaches in our guides: using Elixir's releases with mix release, using Gigalixir, using Fly, and using Heroku. We've also included links to deploying Phoenix on other platforms under Community Deployment Guides. Finally, the release guide has a sample Dockerfile you can use if you prefer to deploy with container technologies.

Let's explore those steps above one by one.

Handling of your application secrets

All Phoenix applications have data that must be kept secure, for example, the username and password for your production database, and the secret Phoenix uses to sign and encrypt important information. The general recommendation is to keep those in environment variables and load them into your application. This is done in config/runtime.exs (formerly config/prod.secret.exs or config/releases.exs), which is responsible for loading secrets and configuration from environment variables.

Therefore, you need to make sure the proper relevant variables are set in production:

$ mix phx.gen.secret
REALLY_LONG_SECRET
$ export SECRET_KEY_BASE=REALLY_LONG_SECRET
$ export DATABASE_URL=ecto://USER:PASS@HOST/database

Do not copy those values directly, set SECRET_KEY_BASE according to the result of mix phx.gen.secret and DATABASE_URL according to your database address.

If for some reason you do not want to rely on environment variables, you can hard code the secrets in your config/runtime.exs but make sure not to check the file into your version control system.

With your secret information properly secured, it is time to configure assets!

Before taking this step, we need to do one bit of preparation. Since we will be readying everything for production, we need to do some setup in that environment by getting our dependencies and compiling.

$ mix deps.get --only prod
$ MIX_ENV=prod mix compile

Compiling your application assets

This step is required only if you have compilable assets like JavaScript and stylesheets. By default, Phoenix uses esbuild but everything is encapsulated in a single mix assets.deploy task defined in your mix.exs:

$ MIX_ENV=prod mix assets.deploy
Check your digested files at "priv/static".

And that is it! The Mix task by default builds the assets and then generates digests with a cache manifest file so Phoenix can quickly serve assets in production.

Note: if you run the task above in your local machine, it will generate many digested assets in priv/static. You can prune them by running mix phx.digest.clean --all.

Keep in mind that, if you by any chance forget to run the steps above, Phoenix will show an error message:

$ PORT=4001 MIX_ENV=prod mix phx.server
10:50:18.732 [info] Running MyAppWeb.Endpoint with Cowboy on http://example.com
10:50:18.735 [error] Could not find static manifest at "my_app/_build/prod/lib/foo/priv/static/cache_manifest.json". Run "mix phx.digest" after building your static files or remove the configuration from "config/prod.exs".

The error message is quite clear: it says Phoenix could not find a static manifest. Just run the commands above to fix it or, if you are not serving or don't care about assets at all, you can just remove the cache_static_manifest configuration from your config.

Starting your server in production

To run Phoenix in production, we need to set the PORT and MIX_ENV environment variables when invoking mix phx.server:

$ PORT=4001 MIX_ENV=prod mix phx.server
10:59:19.136 [info] Running MyAppWeb.Endpoint with Cowboy on http://example.com

To run in detached mode so that the Phoenix server does not stop and continues to run even if you close the terminal:

$ PORT=4001 MIX_ENV=prod elixir --erl "-detached" -S mix phx.server

In case you get an error message, please read it carefully, and open up a bug report if it is still not clear how to address it.

You can also run your application inside an interactive shell:

$ PORT=4001 MIX_ENV=prod iex -S mix phx.server
10:59:19.136 [info] Running MyAppWeb.Endpoint with Cowboy on http://example.com

Putting it all together

The previous sections give an overview about the main steps required to deploy your Phoenix application. In practice, you will end-up adding steps of your own as well. For example, if you are using a database, you will also want to run mix ecto.migrate before starting the server to ensure your database is up to date.

Overall, here is a script you can use as a starting point:

# Initial setup
$ mix deps.get --only prod
$ MIX_ENV=prod mix compile

# Compile assets
$ MIX_ENV=prod mix assets.deploy

# Custom tasks (like DB migrations)
$ MIX_ENV=prod mix ecto.migrate

# Finally run the server
$ PORT=4001 MIX_ENV=prod mix phx.server

And that's it. Next, you can use one of our official guides to deploy:

with Elixir's releases
to Gigalixir, an Elixir-centric Platform as a Service (PaaS)
to Fly.io, a PaaS that deploys your servers close to your users with built-in distribution support
and to Heroku, one of the most popular PaaS.

Community Deployment Guides

Render has first class support for Phoenix applications. There are guides for hosting Phoenix with Mix releases, Distillery, and as a Distributed Elixir Cluster.

Directory structure

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the introductory guides and got a Phoenix application up and running.

When we use mix phx.new to generate a new Phoenix application, it builds a top-level directory structure like this:

├── _build
├── assets
├── config
├── deps
├── lib
│   ├── hello
│   ├── hello.ex
│   ├── hello_web
│   └── hello_web.ex
├── priv
└── test

We will go over those directories one by one:

_build - a directory created by the mix command line tool that ships as part of Elixir that holds all compilation artifacts. As we have seen in "Up and Running", mix is the main interface to your application. We use Mix to compile our code, create databases, run our server, and more. This directory must not be checked into version control and it can be removed at any time. Removing it will force Mix to rebuild your application from scratch.

assets - a directory that keeps source code for your front-end assets, typically JavaScript and CSS. These sources are automatically bundled by the esbuild tool. Static files like images and fonts go in priv/static.

config - a directory that holds your project configuration. The config/config.exs file is the entry point for your configuration. At the end of the config/config.exs, it imports environment specific configuration, which can be found in config/dev.exs, config/test.exs, and config/prod.exs. Finally, config/runtime.exs is executed and it is the best place to read secrets and other dynamic configuration.

deps - a directory with all of our Mix dependencies. You can find all dependencies listed in the mix.exs file, inside the defp deps do function definition. This directory must not be checked into version control and it can be removed at any time. Removing it will force Mix to download all deps from scratch.

lib - a directory that holds your application source code. This directory is broken into two subdirectories, lib/hello and lib/hello_web. The lib/hello directory will be responsible to host all of your business logic and business domain. It typically interacts directly with the database - it is the "Model" in Model-View-Controller (MVC) architecture. lib/hello_web is responsible for exposing your business domain to the world, in this case, through a web application. It holds both the View and Controller from MVC. We will discuss the contents of these directories with more detail in the next sections.

priv - a directory that keeps all resources that are necessary in production but are not directly part of your source code. You typically keep database scripts, translation files, images, and more in here. Generated assets, created from files in the assets directory, are placed in priv/static/assets by default.

test - a directory with all of our application tests. It often mirrors the same structure found in lib.

The lib/hello directory

The lib/hello directory hosts all of your business domain. Since our project does not have any business logic yet, the directory is mostly empty. You will only find three files:

lib/hello
├── application.ex
├── mailer.ex
└── repo.ex

The lib/hello/application.ex file defines an Elixir application named Hello.Application. That's because at the end of the day Phoenix applications are simply Elixir applications. The Hello.Application module defines which services are part of our application:

children = [
  HelloWeb.Telemetry,
  Hello.Repo,
  {Phoenix.PubSub, name: Hello.PubSub},
  HelloWeb.Endpoint
]

If it is your first time with Phoenix, you don't need to worry about the details right now. For now, suffice it to say our application starts a database repository, a PubSub system for sharing messages across processes and nodes, and the application endpoint, which effectively serves HTTP requests. These services are started in the order they are defined and, whenever shutting down your application, they are stopped in the reverse order.

You can learn more about applications in Elixir's official docs for Application.

The lib/hello/mailer.ex file holds the Hello.Mailer module, which defines the main interface to deliver e-mails:

defmodule Hello.Mailer do
  use Swoosh.Mailer, otp_app: :hello
end

In the same lib/hello directory, we will find a lib/hello/repo.ex. It defines a Hello.Repo module which is our main interface to the database. If you are using Postgres (the default database), you will see something like this:

defmodule Hello.Repo do
  use Ecto.Repo,
    otp_app: :hello,
    adapter: Ecto.Adapters.Postgres
end

And that's it for now. As you work on your project, we will add files and modules to this directory.

The lib/hello_web directory

The lib/hello_web directory holds the web-related parts of our application. It looks like this when expanded:

lib/hello_web
├── controllers
│   ├── page_controller.ex
│   ├── page_html.ex
│   ├── error_html.ex
│   ├── error_json.ex
│   └── page_html
│       └── home.html.heex
├── components
│   ├── core_components.ex
│   ├── layouts.ex
│   └── layouts
│       ├── app.html.heex
│       └── root.html.heex
├── endpoint.ex
├── gettext.ex
├── router.ex
└── telemetry.ex

All of the files which are currently in the controllers and components directories are there to create the "Welcome to Phoenix!" page we saw in the "Up and running" guide.

By looking at controller and components directories, we can see Phoenix provides features for handling layouts and HTML and error pages out of the box.

Besides the directories mentioned, lib/hello_web has four files at its root. lib/hello_web/endpoint.ex is the entry-point for HTTP requests. Once the browser accesses http://localhost:4000, the endpoint starts processing the data, eventually leading to the router, which is defined in lib/hello_web/router.ex. The router defines the rules to dispatch requests to "controllers", which calls a view module to render HTML pages back to clients. We explore these layers in length in other guides, starting with the "Request life-cycle" guide coming next.

Through Telemetry, Phoenix is able to collect metrics and send monitoring events of your application. The lib/hello_web/telemetry.ex file defines the supervisor responsible for managing the telemetry processes. You can find more information on this topic in the Telemetry guide.

Finally, there is a lib/hello_web/gettext.ex file which provides internationalization through Gettext. If you are not worried about internationalization, you can safely skip this file and its contents.

The assets directory

The assets directory contains source files related to front-end assets, such as JavaScript and CSS. Since Phoenix v1.6, we use esbuild to compile assets, which is managed by the esbuild Elixir package. The integration with esbuild is baked into your app. The relevant config can be found in your config/config.exs file.

Your other static assets are placed in the priv/static folder, where priv/static/assets is kept for generated assets. Everything in priv/static is served by the Plug.Static plug configured in lib/hello_web/endpoint.ex. When running in dev mode (MIX_ENV=dev), Phoenix watches for any changes you make in the assets directory, and then takes care of updating your front end application in your browser as you work.

Note that when you first create your Phoenix app using mix phx.new it is possible to specify options that will affect the presence and layout of the assets directory. In fact, Phoenix apps can bring their own front end tools or not have a front-end at all (handy if you're writing an API for example). For more information you can run mix help phx.new or see the documentation in Mix tasks.

If the default esbuild integration does not cover your needs, for example because you want to use another build tool, you can switch to a custom assets build.

As for CSS, Phoenix ships with the Tailwind CSS Framework, providing a base setup for projects. You may move to any CSS framework of your choice. Additional references can be found in the asset management guide.

Deploying on Heroku

What we'll need

The only thing we'll need for this guide is a working Phoenix application. For those of us who need a simple application to deploy, please follow the Up and Running guide.

Goals

Our main goal for this guide is to get a Phoenix application running on Heroku.

Limitations

Heroku is a great platform and Elixir performs well on it. However, you may run into limitations if you plan to leverage advanced features provided by Elixir and Phoenix, such as:

Connections are limited.

Heroku limits the number of simultaneous connections as well as the duration of each connection. It is common to use Elixir for real-time apps which need lots of concurrent, persistent connections, and Phoenix is capable of handling over 2 million connections on a single server.

Distributed clustering is not possible.

Heroku firewalls dynos off from one another. This means things like distributed Phoenix channels and distributed tasks will need to rely on something like Redis instead of Elixir's built-in distribution.

In-memory state such as those in Agents, GenServers, and ETS will be lost every 24 hours.

Heroku restarts dynos every 24 hours regardless of whether the node is healthy.

The built-in observer can't be used with Heroku.

Heroku does allow for connection into your dyno, but you won't be able to use the observer to watch the state of your dyno.

If you are just getting started, or you don't expect to use the features above, Heroku should be enough for your needs. For instance, if you are migrating an existing application running on Heroku to Phoenix, keeping a similar set of features, Elixir will perform just as well or even better than your current stack.

If you want a platform-as-a-service without these limitations, try Gigalixir. If you would rather deploy to a cloud platform, such as EC2, Google Cloud, etc, consider using mix release.

Steps

Let's separate this process into a few steps, so we can keep track of where we are.

Initialize Git repository
Sign up for Heroku
Install the Heroku Toolbelt
Create and set up Heroku application
Make our project ready for Heroku
Deploy time!
Useful Heroku commands

Initializing Git repository

Git is a popular decentralized revision control system and is also used to deploy apps to Heroku.

Before we can push to Heroku, we'll need to initialize a local Git repository and commit our files to it. We can do so by running the following commands in our project directory:

$ git init
$ git add .
$ git commit -m "Initial commit"

Heroku offers some great information on how it is using Git here.

Signing up for Heroku

Signing up to Heroku is very simple, just head over to https://signup.heroku.com/ and fill in the form.

The Free plan will give us one web dyno and one worker dyno, as well as a PostgreSQL and Redis instance for free.

These are meant to be used for testing and development, and come with some limitations. In order to run a production application, please consider upgrading to a paid plan.

Installing the Heroku Toolbelt

Once we have signed up, we can download the correct version of the Heroku Toolbelt for our system here.

The Heroku CLI, part of the Toolbelt, is useful to create Heroku applications, list currently running dynos for an existing application, tail logs or run one-off commands (mix tasks for instance).

Create and Set Up Heroku Application

There are two different ways to deploy a Phoenix app on Heroku. We could use Heroku buildpacks or their container stack. The difference between these two approaches is in how we tell Heroku to treat our build. In buildpack case, we need to update our apps configuration on Heroku to use Phoenix/Elixir specific buildpacks. On container approach, we have more control on how we want to set up our app, and we can define our container image using Dockerfile and heroku.yml. This section will explore the buildpack approach. In order to use Dockerfile, it is often recommended to convert our app to use releases, which we will describe later on.

Create Application

A buildpack is a convenient way of packaging framework and/or runtime support. Phoenix requires 2 buildpacks to run on Heroku, the first adds basic Elixir support and the second adds Phoenix specific commands.

With the Toolbelt installed, let's create the Heroku application. We will do so using the latest available version of the Elixir buildpack:

$ heroku create --buildpack hashnuke/elixir
Creating app... done, ⬢ mysterious-meadow-6277
Setting buildpack to hashnuke/elixir... done
https://mysterious-meadow-6277.herokuapp.com/ | https://git.heroku.com/mysterious-meadow-6277.git

Note: the first time we use a Heroku command, it may prompt us to log in. If this happens, just enter the email and password you specified during signup.

Note: the name of the Heroku application is the random string after "Creating" in the output above (mysterious-meadow-6277). This will be unique, so expect to see a different name from "mysterious-meadow-6277".

Note: the URL in the output is the URL to our application. If we open it in our browser now, we will get the default Heroku welcome page.

Note: if we hadn't initialized our Git repository before we ran the heroku create command, we wouldn't have our Heroku remote repository properly set up at this point. We can set that up manually by running: heroku git:remote -a [our-app-name].

The buildpack uses a predefined Elixir and Erlang version, but to avoid surprises when deploying, it is best to explicitly list the Elixir and Erlang version we want in production to be the same we are using during development or in your continuous integration servers. This is done by creating a config file named elixir_buildpack.config in the root directory of your project with your target version of Elixir and Erlang:

# Elixir version
elixir_version=1.14.0

# Erlang version
# https://github.com/HashNuke/heroku-buildpack-elixir-otp-builds/blob/master/otp-versions
erlang_version=24.3

# Invoke assets.deploy defined in your mix.exs to deploy assets with esbuild
# Note we nuke the esbuild executable from the image
hook_post_compile="eval mix assets.deploy && rm -f _build/esbuild*"

Finally, let's tell the build pack how to start our webserver. Create a file named Procfile at the root of your project:

web: mix phx.server

Optional: Node, npm, and the Phoenix Static buildpack

By default, Phoenix uses esbuild and manages all assets for you. However, if you are using node and npm, you will need to install the Phoenix Static buildpack to handle them:

$ heroku buildpacks:add https://github.com/gigalixir/gigalixir-buildpack-phoenix-static.git
Buildpack added. Next release on mysterious-meadow-6277 will use:
  1. https://github.com/HashNuke/heroku-buildpack-elixir.git
  2. https://github.com/gigalixir/gigalixir-heroku-buildpack-phoenix-static.git

When using this buildpack, you want to delegate all asset bundling to npm. So you must remove the hook_post_compile configuration from your elixir_buildpack.config and move it to the deploy script of your assets/package.json. Something like this:

{
  ...
  "scripts": {
    "deploy": "cd .. && mix assets.deploy && rm -f _build/esbuild*"
  }
  ...
}

The Phoenix Static buildpack uses a predefined Node.js version, but to avoid surprises when deploying, it is best to explicitly list the Node.js version we want in production to be the same we are using during development or in your continuous integration servers. This is done by creating a config file named phoenix_static_buildpack.config in the root directory of your project with your target version of Node.js:

# Node.js version
node_version=10.20.1

Please refer to the configuration section for full details. You can make your own custom build script, but for now we will use the default one provided.

Finally, note that since we are using multiple buildpacks, you might run into an issue where the sequence is out of order (the Elixir buildpack needs to run before the Phoenix Static buildpack). Heroku's docs explain this better, but you will need to make sure the Phoenix Static buildpack comes last.

Making our Project ready for Heroku

Every new Phoenix project ships with a config file config/runtime.exs (formerly config/prod.secret.exs) which loads configuration and secrets from environment variables. This aligns well with Heroku best practices (12-factor apps), so the only work left for us to do is to configure URLs and SSL.

First let's tell Phoenix to only use the SSL version of the website. Find the endpoint config in your config/prod.exs:

config :scaffold, ScaffoldWeb.Endpoint,
  url: [port: 443, scheme: "https"],

... and add force_ssl

config :scaffold, ScaffoldWeb.Endpoint,
  url: [port: 443, scheme: "https"],
  force_ssl: [rewrite_on: [:x_forwarded_proto]],

force_ssl need to be set here because it is a compile time config. It will not work when set from runtime.exs.

Then in your config/runtime.exs (formerly config/prod.secret.exs):

... add host

config :scaffold, ScaffoldWeb.Endpoint,
  url: [host: host, port: 443, scheme: "https"]

and uncomment the # ssl: true, line in your repository configuration. It will look like this:

config :hello, Hello.Repo,
  ssl: true,
  url: database_url,
  pool_size: String.to_integer(System.get_env("POOL_SIZE") || "10")

Finally, if you plan on using websockets, then we will need to decrease the timeout for the websocket transport in lib/hello_web/endpoint.ex. If you do not plan on using websockets, then leaving it set to false is fine. You can find further explanation of the options available at the documentation.

defmodule HelloWeb.Endpoint do
  use Phoenix.Endpoint, otp_app: :hello

  socket "/socket", HelloWeb.UserSocket,
    websocket: [timeout: 45_000]

  ...
end

Also set the host in Heroku:

$ heroku config:set PHX_HOST="mysterious-meadow-6277.herokuapp.com"

This ensures that any idle connections are closed by Phoenix before they reach Heroku's 55-second timeout window.

Creating Environment Variables in Heroku

The DATABASE_URL config var is automatically created by Heroku when we add the Heroku Postgres add-on. We can create the database via the Heroku toolbelt:

$ heroku addons:create heroku-postgresql:mini

Now we set the POOL_SIZE config var:

$ heroku config:set POOL_SIZE=18

This value should be just under the number of available connections, leaving a couple open for migrations and mix tasks. The mini database allows 20 connections, so we set this number to 18. If additional dynos will share the database, reduce the POOL_SIZE to give each dyno an equal share.

When running a mix task later (after we have pushed the project to Heroku) you will also want to limit its pool size like so:

$ heroku run "POOL_SIZE=2 mix hello.task"

So that Ecto does not attempt to open more than the available connections.

We still have to create the SECRET_KEY_BASE config based on a random string. First, use mix phx.gen.secret to get a new secret:

$ mix phx.gen.secret
xvafzY4y01jYuzLm3ecJqo008dVnU3CN4f+MamNd1Zue4pXvfvUjbiXT8akaIF53

Your random string will be different; don't use this example value.

Now set it in Heroku:

$ heroku config:set SECRET_KEY_BASE="xvafzY4y01jYuzLm3ecJqo008dVnU3CN4f+MamNd1Zue4pXvfvUjbiXT8akaIF53"
Setting config vars and restarting mysterious-meadow-6277... done, v3
SECRET_KEY_BASE: xvafzY4y01jYuzLm3ecJqo008dVnU3CN4f+MamNd1Zue4pXvfvUjbiXT8akaIF53

Deploy Time!

Our project is now ready to be deployed on Heroku.

Let's commit all our changes:

$ git add elixir_buildpack.config
$ git commit -a -m "Use production config from Heroku ENV variables and decrease socket timeout"

And deploy:

$ git push heroku main
Counting objects: 55, done.
Delta compression using up to 8 threads.
Compressing objects: 100% (49/49), done.
Writing objects: 100% (55/55), 48.48 KiB | 0 bytes/s, done.
Total 55 (delta 1), reused 0 (delta 0)
remote: Compressing source files... done.
remote: Building source:
remote:
remote: -----> Multipack app detected
remote: -----> Fetching custom git buildpack... done
remote: -----> elixir app detected
remote: -----> Checking Erlang and Elixir versions
remote:        WARNING: elixir_buildpack.config wasn't found in the app
remote:        Using default config from Elixir buildpack
remote:        Will use the following versions:
remote:        * Stack cedar-14
remote:        * Erlang 17.5
remote:        * Elixir 1.0.4
remote:        Will export the following config vars:
remote:        * Config vars DATABASE_URL
remote:        * MIX_ENV=prod
remote: -----> Stack changed, will rebuild
remote: -----> Fetching Erlang 17.5
remote: -----> Installing Erlang 17.5 (changed)
remote:
remote: -----> Fetching Elixir v1.0.4
remote: -----> Installing Elixir v1.0.4 (changed)
remote: -----> Installing Hex
remote: 2015-07-07 00:04:00 URL:https://s3.amazonaws.com/s3.hex.pm/installs/1.0.0/hex.ez [262010/262010] ->
"/app/.mix/archives/hex.ez" [1]
remote: * creating /app/.mix/archives/hex.ez
remote: -----> Installing rebar
remote: * creating /app/.mix/rebar
remote: -----> Fetching app dependencies with mix
remote: Running dependency resolution
remote: Dependency resolution completed successfully
remote: [...]
remote: -----> Compiling
remote: [...]
remote: Generated phoenix_heroku app
remote: [...]
remote: Consolidated protocols written to _build/prod/consolidated
remote: -----> Creating .profile.d with env vars
remote: -----> Fetching custom git buildpack... done
remote: -----> Phoenix app detected
remote:
remote: -----> Loading configuration and environment
remote:        Loading config...
remote:        [...]
remote:        Will export the following config vars:
remote:        * Config vars DATABASE_URL
remote:        * MIX_ENV=prod
remote:
remote: -----> Compressing... done, 82.1MB
remote: -----> Launching... done, v5
remote:        https://mysterious-meadow-6277.herokuapp.com/ deployed to Heroku
remote:
remote: Verifying deploy... done.
To https://git.heroku.com/mysterious-meadow-6277.git
 * [new branch]      master -> master

Typing heroku open in the terminal should launch a browser with the Phoenix welcome page opened. In the event that you are using Ecto to access a database, you will also need to run migrations after the first deploy:

$ heroku run "POOL_SIZE=2 mix ecto.migrate"

And that's it!

Deploying to Heroku using the container stack

Create Heroku application

Set the stack of your app to container, this allows us to use Dockerfile to define our app setup.

$ heroku create
Creating app... done, ⬢ mysterious-meadow-6277
$ heroku stack:set container

Add a new heroku.yml file to your root folder. In this file you can define addons used by your app, how to build the image and what configs are passed to the image. You can learn more about Heroku's heroku.yml options here. Here is a sample:

setup:
  addons:
    - plan: heroku-postgresql
      as: DATABASE
build:
  docker:
    web: Dockerfile
  config:
    MIX_ENV: prod
    SECRET_KEY_BASE: $SECRET_KEY_BASE
    DATABASE_URL: $DATABASE_URL

Set up releases and Dockerfile

Now we need to define a Dockerfile at the root folder of your project that contains your application. We recommend to use releases when doing so, as the release will allow us to build a container with only the parts of Erlang and Elixir we actually use. Follow the releases docs. At the end of the guide, there is a sample Dockerfile file you can use.

Once you have the image definition set up, you can push your app to heroku and you can see it starts building the image and deploy it.

Useful Heroku Commands

We can look at the logs of our application by running the following command in our project directory:

$ heroku logs # use --tail if you want to tail them

We can also start an IEx session attached to our terminal for experimenting in our app's environment:

$ heroku run "POOL_SIZE=2 iex -S mix"

In fact, we can run anything using the heroku run command, like the Ecto migration task from above:

$ heroku run "POOL_SIZE=2 mix ecto.migrate"

Connecting to your dyno

Heroku gives you the ability to connect to your dyno with an IEx shell which allows running Elixir code such as database queries.

Modify the web process in your Procfile to run a named node:

web: elixir --sname server -S mix phx.server

Redeploy to Heroku

Connect to the dyno with heroku ps:exec (if you have several applications on the same repository you will need to specify the app name or the remote name with --app APP_NAME or --remote REMOTE_NAME)

Launch an iex session with iex --sname console --remsh server

You have an iex session into your dyno!

Troubleshooting

Compilation Error

Occasionally, an application will compile locally, but not on Heroku. The compilation error on Heroku will look something like this:

remote: == Compilation error on file lib/postgrex/connection.ex ==
remote: could not compile dependency :postgrex, "mix compile" failed. You can recompile this dependency with "mix deps.compile postgrex", update it with "mix deps.update postgrex" or clean it with "mix deps.clean postgrex"
remote: ** (CompileError) lib/postgrex/connection.ex:207: Postgrex.Connection.__struct__/0 is undefined, cannot expand struct Postgrex.Connection
remote:     (elixir) src/elixir_map.erl:58: :elixir_map.translate_struct/4
remote:     (stdlib) lists.erl:1353: :lists.mapfoldl/3
remote:     (stdlib) lists.erl:1354: :lists.mapfoldl/3
remote:
remote:
remote:  !     Push rejected, failed to compile elixir app
remote:
remote: Verifying deploy...
remote:
remote: !   Push rejected to mysterious-meadow-6277.
remote:
To https://git.heroku.com/mysterious-meadow-6277.git

This has to do with stale dependencies which are not getting recompiled properly. It's possible to force Heroku to recompile all dependencies on each deploy, which should fix this problem. The way to do it is to add a new file called elixir_buildpack.config at the root of the application. The file should contain this line:

always_rebuild=true

Commit this file to the repository and try to push again to Heroku.

Connection Timeout Error

If you are constantly getting connection timeouts while running heroku run this could mean that your internet provider has blocked port number 5000:

heroku run "POOL_SIZE=2 mix myapp.task"
Running POOL_SIZE=2 mix myapp.task on mysterious-meadow-6277... !
ETIMEDOUT: connect ETIMEDOUT 50.19.103.36:5000

You can overcome this by adding detached option to run command:

heroku run:detached "POOL_SIZE=2 mix ecto.migrate"
Running POOL_SIZE=2 mix ecto.migrate on mysterious-meadow-6277... done, run.8089 (Free)

Installation

In order to build a Phoenix application, we will need a few dependencies installed in our Operating System:

the Erlang VM and the Elixir programming language
a database - Phoenix recommends PostgreSQL, but you can pick others or not use a database at all
and other optional packages.

Please take a look at this list and make sure to install anything necessary for your system. Having dependencies installed in advance can prevent frustrating problems later on.

Elixir 1.14 or later

Phoenix is written in Elixir, and our application code will also be written in Elixir. We won't get far in a Phoenix app without it! The Elixir site maintains a great Installation Page to help.

Erlang 24 or later

Elixir code compiles to Erlang byte code to run on the Erlang virtual machine. Without Erlang, Elixir code has no virtual machine to run on, so we need to install Erlang as well.

When we install Elixir using instructions from the Elixir Installation Page, we will usually get Erlang too. If Erlang was not installed along with Elixir, please see the Erlang Instructions section of the Elixir Installation Page for instructions.

Phoenix

To check that we are on Elixir 1.14 and Erlang 24 or later, run:

elixir -v
Erlang/OTP 24 [erts-12.0] [source] [64-bit] [smp:8:8] [async-threads:10] [hipe] [kernel-poll:false] [dtrace]

Elixir 1.14.0

Once we have Elixir and Erlang, we are ready to install the Phoenix application generator:

$ mix archive.install hex phx_new

The phx.new generator is now available to generate new applications in the next guide, called Up and Running. The flags mentioned below are command line options to the generator; see all available options by calling mix help phx.new.

PostgreSQL

PostgreSQL is a relational database server. Phoenix configures applications to use it by default, but we can switch to MySQL, MSSQL, or SQLite3 by passing the --database flag when creating a new application.

In order to talk to databases, Phoenix applications use another Elixir package, called Ecto. If you don't plan to use databases in your application, you can pass the --no-ecto flag.

However, if you are just getting started with Phoenix, we recommend you to install PostgreSQL and make sure it is running. The PostgreSQL wiki has installation guides for a number of different systems.

inotify-tools (for Linux users)

Phoenix provides a very handy feature called Live Reloading. As you change your views or your assets, it automatically reloads the page in the browser. In order for this functionality to work, you need a filesystem watcher.

macOS and Windows users already have a filesystem watcher, but Linux users must install inotify-tools. Please consult the inotify-tools wiki for distribution-specific installation instructions.

Summary

At the end of this section, you must have installed Elixir, Hex, Phoenix, and PostgreSQL. Now that we have everything installed, let's create our first Phoenix application and get up and running.

mix phx.gen.auth

Generates authentication logic and related views for a resource.

$ mix phx.gen.auth Accounts User users

The first argument is the context module followed by the schema module and its plural name (used as the schema table name).

Additional information and security considerations are detailed in the mix phx.gen.auth guide.

LiveView vs conventional Controllers & Views

Authentication views can either be generated to use LiveView by passing the --live option, or they can use conventional Phoenix Controllers & Views by passing --no-live.

If neither of these options are provided, a prompt will be displayed.

Using the --live option is advised if you plan on using LiveView elsewhere in your application. The user experience when navigating between LiveViews can be tightly controlled, allowing you to let your users navigate to authentication views without necessarily triggering a new HTTP request each time (which would result in a full page load).

Password hashing

The password hashing mechanism defaults to bcrypt for Unix systems and pbkdf2 for Windows systems. Both systems use the Comeonin interface.

The password hashing mechanism can be overridden with the --hashing-lib option. The following values are supported:

bcrypt - bcrypt_elixir
pbkdf2 - pbkdf2_elixir
argon2 - argon2_elixir

We recommend developers to consider using argon2, which is the most robust of all 3. The downside is that argon2 is quite CPU and memory intensive, and you will need more powerful instances to run your applications on.

For more information about choosing these libraries, see the Comeonin project.

Web namespace

By default, the controllers and HTML view will be namespaced by the schema name. You can customize the web module namespace by passing the --web flag with a module name, for example:

$ mix phx.gen.auth Accounts User users --web Warehouse

Which would generate the controllers, views, templates and associated tests nested in the MyAppWeb.Warehouse namespace:

lib/my_app_web/controllers/warehouse/user_auth.ex
lib/my_app_web/controllers/warehouse/user_confirmation_controller.ex
lib/my_app_web/controllers/warehouse/user_confirmation_html.ex
lib/my_app_web/controllers/warehouse/user_confirmation_html/new.html.heex
test/my_app_web/controllers/warehouse/user_auth_test.exs
test/my_app_web/controllers/warehouse/user_confirmation_controller_test.exs
and so on...

Multiple invocations

You can invoke this generator multiple times. This is typically useful if you have distinct resources that go through distinct authentication workflows:

$ mix phx.gen.auth Store User users
$ mix phx.gen.auth Backoffice Admin admins

Binary ids

The --binary-id option causes the generated migration to use binary_id for its primary key and foreign keys.

Default options

This generator uses default options provided in the :generators configuration of your application. These are the defaults:

config :your_app, :generators,
  binary_id: false,
  sample_binary_id: "11111111-1111-1111-1111-111111111111"

You can override those options per invocation by providing corresponding switches, e.g. --no-binary-id to use normal ids despite the default configuration.

Custom table names

By default, the table name for the migration and schema will be the plural name provided for the resource. To customize this value, a --table option may be provided. For example:

$ mix phx.gen.auth Accounts User users --table accounts_users

This will cause the generated tables to be named "accounts_users" and "accounts_users_tokens".

mix phx.gen.context

Generates a context with functions around an Ecto schema.

$ mix phx.gen.context Accounts User users name:string age:integer

The first argument is the context module followed by the schema module and its plural name (used as the schema table name).

The context is an Elixir module that serves as an API boundary for the given resource. A context often holds many related resources. Therefore, if the context already exists, it will be augmented with functions for the given resource.

Note: A resource may also be split over distinct contexts (such as Accounts.User and Payments.User).

The schema is responsible for mapping the database fields into an Elixir struct.

Overall, this generator will add the following files to lib/your_app:

a context module in accounts.ex, serving as the API boundary
a schema in accounts/user.ex, with a users table

A migration file for the repository and test files for the context will also be generated.

Generating without a schema

In some cases, you may wish to bootstrap the context module and tests, but leave internal implementation of the context and schema to yourself. Use the --no-schema flags to accomplish this.

table

By default, the table name for the migration and schema will be the plural name provided for the resource. To customize this value, a --table option may be provided. For example:

$ mix phx.gen.context Accounts User users --table cms_users

binary_id

Generated migration can use binary_id for schema's primary key and its references with option --binary-id.

Default options

This generator uses default options provided in the :generators configuration of your application. These are the defaults:

config :your_app, :generators,
  migration: true,
  binary_id: false,
  timestamp_type: :naive_datetime,
  sample_binary_id: "11111111-1111-1111-1111-111111111111"

You can override those options per invocation by providing corresponding switches, e.g. --no-binary-id to use normal ids despite the default configuration or --migration to force generation of the migration.

Read the documentation for phx.gen.schema for more information on attributes.

Skipping prompts

This generator will prompt you if there is an existing context with the same name, in order to provide more instructions on how to correctly use phoenix contexts. You can skip this prompt and automatically merge the new schema access functions and tests into the existing context using --merge-with-existing-context. To prevent changes to the existing context and exit the generator, use --no-merge-with-existing-context.

mix phx.gen.html

Generates controller with view, templates, schema and context for an HTML resource.

mix phx.gen.html Accounts User users name:string age:integer

The first argument, Accounts, is the resource's context. A context is an Elixir module that serves as an API boundary for closely related resources.

The second argument, User, is the resource's schema. A schema is an Elixir module responsible for mapping database fields into an Elixir struct. The User schema above specifies two fields with their respective colon-delimited data types: name:string and age:integer. See mix phx.gen.schema for more information on attributes.

Note: A resource may also be split over distinct contexts (such as Accounts.User and Payments.User).

This generator adds the following files to lib/:

a controller in lib/my_app_web/controllers/user_controller.ex
default CRUD HTML templates in lib/my_app_web/controllers/user_html
an HTML view collocated with the controller in lib/my_app_web/controllers/user_html.ex
a schema in lib/my_app/accounts/user.ex, with an users table
a context module in lib/my_app/accounts.ex for the accounts API

Additionally, this generator creates the following files:

a migration for the schema in priv/repo/migrations
a controller test module in test/my_app/controllers/user_controller_test.exs
a context test module in test/my_app/accounts_test.exs
a context test helper module in test/support/fixtures/accounts_fixtures.ex

If the context already exists, this generator injects functions for the given resource into the context, context test, and context test helper modules.

Umbrella app configuration

By default, Phoenix injects both web and domain specific functionality into the same application. When using umbrella applications, those concerns are typically broken into two separate apps, your context application - let's call it my_app - and its web layer, which Phoenix assumes to be my_app_web.

You can teach Phoenix to use this style via the :context_app configuration option in your my_app_umbrella/config/config.exs:

config :my_app_web,
  ecto_repos: [Stuff.Repo],
  generators: [context_app: :my_app]

Alternatively, the --context-app option may be supplied to the generator:

mix phx.gen.html Sales User users --context-app my_app

If you delete the :context_app configuration option, Phoenix will automatically put generated web files in my_app_umbrella/apps/my_app_web_web.

If you change the value of :context_app to :new_value, my_app_umbrella/apps/new_value_web must already exist or you will get the following error:

** (Mix) no directory for context_app :new_value found in my_app_web's deps.

Web namespace

By default, the controller and HTML view will be namespaced by the schema name. You can customize the web module namespace by passing the --web flag with a module name, for example:

mix phx.gen.html Sales User users --web Sales

Which would generate a lib/app_web/controllers/sales/user_controller.ex and lib/app_web/controllers/sales/user_html.ex.

Customizing the context, schema, tables and migrations

In some cases, you may wish to bootstrap HTML templates, controllers, and controller tests, but leave internal implementation of the context or schema to yourself. You can use the --no-context and --no-schema flags for file generation control.

You can also change the table name or configure the migrations to use binary ids for primary keys, see mix phx.gen.schema for more information.

mix phx.gen.json

Generates controller, JSON view, and context for a JSON resource.

mix phx.gen.json Accounts User users name:string age:integer

The first argument is the context module followed by the schema module and its plural name (used as the schema table name).

The context is an Elixir module that serves as an API boundary for the given resource. A context often holds many related resources. Therefore, if the context already exists, it will be augmented with functions for the given resource.

Note: A resource may also be split over distinct contexts (such as Accounts.User and Payments.User).

The schema is responsible for mapping the database fields into an Elixir struct. It is followed by an optional list of attributes, with their respective names and types. See mix phx.gen.schema for more information on attributes.

Overall, this generator will add the following files to lib/:

a context module in lib/app/accounts.ex for the accounts API
a schema in lib/app/accounts/user.ex, with an users table
a controller in lib/app_web/controllers/user_controller.ex
a JSON view collocated with the controller in lib/app_web/controllers/user_json.ex

A migration file for the repository and test files for the context and controller features will also be generated.

API Prefix

By default, the prefix "/api" will be generated for API route paths. This can be customized via the :api_prefix generators configuration:

config :your_app, :generators,
  api_prefix: "/api/v1"

The context app

The location of the web files (controllers, json views, etc) in an umbrella application will vary based on the :context_app config located in your applications :generators configuration. When set, the Phoenix generators will generate web files directly in your lib and test folders since the application is assumed to be isolated to web specific functionality. If :context_app is not set, the generators will place web related lib and test files in a web/ directory since the application is assumed to be handling both web and domain specific functionality. Example configuration:

config :my_app_web, :generators, context_app: :my_app

Alternatively, the --context-app option may be supplied to the generator:

mix phx.gen.json Sales User users --context-app warehouse

Web namespace

By default, the controller and json view will be namespaced by the schema name. You can customize the web module namespace by passing the --web flag with a module name, for example:

mix phx.gen.json Sales User users --web Sales

Which would generate a lib/app_web/controllers/sales/user_controller.ex and lib/app_web/controller/sales/user_json.ex.

Customizing the context, schema, tables and migrations

In some cases, you may wish to bootstrap JSON views, controllers, and controller tests, but leave internal implementation of the context or schema to yourself. You can use the --no-context and --no-schema flags for file generation control.

You can also change the table name or configure the migrations to use binary ids for primary keys, see mix phx.gen.schema for more information.

mix phx.gen.schema

Generates an Ecto schema and migration.

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts title:string views:integer

The first argument is the schema module followed by its plural name (used as the table name).

The generated schema above will contain:

a schema file in lib/my_app/blog/post.ex, with a blog_posts table
a migration file for the repository

The generated migration can be skipped with --no-migration.

Contexts

Your schemas can be generated and added to a separate OTP app. Make sure your configuration is properly setup or manually specify the context app with the --context-app option with the CLI.

Via config:

config :marketing_web, :generators, context_app: :marketing

Via CLI:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts title:string views:integer --context-app marketing

Attributes

The resource fields are given using name:type syntax where type are the types supported by Ecto. Omitting the type makes it default to :string:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts title views:integer

The following types are supported:

:integer

:float

:decimal

:boolean

:map

:string

:array

:references

:text

:date

:time

:time_usec

:naive_datetime

:naive_datetime_usec

:utc_datetime

:utc_datetime_usec

:uuid

:binary

:enum

:datetime - An alias for :naive_datetime

The generator also supports references, which we will properly associate the given column to the primary key column of the referenced table:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts title user_id:references:users

This will result in a migration with an :integer column of :user_id and create an index.

Furthermore an array type can also be given if it is supported by your database, although it requires the type of the underlying array element to be given too:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts tags:array:string

Unique columns can be automatically generated by using:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts title:unique unique_int:integer:unique

Redact columns can be automatically generated by using:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Accounts.Superhero superheroes secret_identity:redact password:string:redact

Ecto.Enum fields can be generated by using:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post blog_posts title status:enum:unpublished:published:deleted

If no data type is given, it defaults to a string.

table

By default, the table name for the migration and schema will be the plural name provided for the resource. To customize this value, a --table option may be provided. For example:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post posts --table cms_posts

binary_id

Generated migration can use binary_id for schema's primary key and its references with option --binary-id.

repo

Generated migration can use repo to set the migration repository folder with option --repo:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post posts --repo MyApp.Repo.Auth

migration_dir

Generated migrations can be added to a specific --migration-dir which sets the migration folder path:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post posts --migration-dir /path/to/directory

prefix

By default migrations and schemas are generated without a prefix.

For PostgreSQL this sets the "SCHEMA" (typically set via search_path) and for MySQL it sets the database for the generated migration and schema. The prefix can be used to thematically organize your tables on the database level.

A prefix can be specified with the --prefix flags. For example:

$ mix phx.gen.schema Blog.Post posts --prefix blog

Warning

The flag does not generate migrations to create the schema / database. This needs to be done manually or in a separate migration.

Default options

This generator uses default options provided in the :generators configuration of your application. These are the defaults:

config :your_app, :generators,
  migration: true,
  binary_id: false,
  timestamp_type: :naive_datetime,
  sample_binary_id: "11111111-1111-1111-1111-111111111111"

You can override those options per invocation by providing corresponding switches, e.g. --no-binary-id to use normal ids despite the default configuration or --migration to force generation of the migration.

UTC timestamps

By setting the :timestamp_type to :utc_datetime, the timestamps will be created using the UTC timezone. This results in a DateTime struct instead of a NaiveDateTime. This can also be set to :utc_datetime_usec for microsecond precision.

mix phx.new

Creates a new Phoenix project.

It expects the path of the project as an argument.

$ mix phx.new PATH [--module MODULE] [--app APP]

A project at the given PATH will be created. The application name and module name will be retrieved from the path, unless --module or --app is given.

Options

--umbrella - generate an umbrella project, with one application for your domain, and a second application for the web interface.

--app - the name of the OTP application

--module - the name of the base module in the generated skeleton

--database - specify the database adapter for Ecto. One of:

postgres - via https://github.com/elixir-ecto/postgrex
mysql - via https://github.com/elixir-ecto/myxql
mssql - via https://github.com/livehelpnow/tds
sqlite3 - via https://github.com/elixir-sqlite/ecto_sqlite3

Please check the driver docs for more information and requirements. Defaults to "postgres".

--adapter - specify the http adapter. One of:

cowboy - via https://github.com/elixir-plug/plug_cowboy
bandit - via https://github.com/mtrudel/bandit

Please check the adapter docs for more information and requirements. Defaults to "bandit".

--no-assets - equivalent to --no-esbuild and --no-tailwind

--no-dashboard - do not include Phoenix.LiveDashboard

--no-ecto - do not generate Ecto files

--no-esbuild - do not include esbuild dependencies and assets. We do not recommend setting this option, unless for API only applications, as doing so requires you to manually add and track JavaScript dependencies

--no-gettext - do not generate gettext files

--no-html - do not generate HTML views

--no-live - comment out LiveView socket setup in your Endpoint and assets/js/app.js. Automatically disabled if --no-html is given

--no-mailer - do not generate Swoosh mailer files

--no-tailwind - do not include tailwind dependencies and assets. The generated markup will still include Tailwind CSS classes, those are left-in as reference for the subsequent styling of your layout and components

--binary-id - use binary_id as primary key type in Ecto schemas

--verbose - use verbose output

-v, --version - prints the Phoenix installer version

When passing the --no-ecto flag, Phoenix generators such as phx.gen.html, phx.gen.json, phx.gen.live, and phx.gen.context may no longer work as expected as they generate context files that rely on Ecto for the database access. In those cases, you can pass the --no-context flag to generate most of the HTML and JSON files but skip the context, allowing you to fill in the blanks as desired.

Similarly, if --no-html is given, the files generated by phx.gen.html will no longer work, as important HTML components will be missing.

Installation

mix phx.new by default prompts you to fetch and install your dependencies. You can enable this behaviour by passing the --install flag or disable it with the --no-install flag.

Examples

$ mix phx.new hello_world

Is equivalent to:

$ mix phx.new hello_world --module HelloWorld

Or without the HTML and JS bits (useful for APIs):

$ mix phx.new ~/Workspace/hello_world --no-html --no-assets

As an umbrella:

$ mix phx.new hello --umbrella

Would generate the following directory structure and modules:

hello_umbrella/   Hello.Umbrella
  apps/
    hello/        Hello
    hello_web/    HelloWeb

You can read more about umbrella projects using the official Elixir guide

PHX_NEW_CACHE_DIR

In rare cases, it may be useful to copy the build from a previously cached build. To do this, set the PHX_NEW_CACHE_DIR environment variable before running mix phx.new. For example, you could generate a cache by running:

mix phx.new mycache --no-install && cd mycache   && mix deps.get && mix deps.compile && mix assets.setup   && rm -rf assets config lib priv test mix.exs README.md

Your cached build directory should contain:

_build
deps
mix.lock

Then you could run:

PHX_NEW_CACHE_DIR=/path/to/mycache mix phx.new myapp

The entire cache directory will be copied to the new project, replacing any existing files where conflicts exist.

mix phx.gen.auth

The mix phx.gen.auth command generates a flexible, pre-built authentication system into your Phoenix app. This generator allows you to quickly move past the task of adding authentication to your codebase and stay focused on the real-world problem your application is trying to solve.

Getting started

Before running this command, consider committing your work as it generates multiple files.

Let's start by running the following command from the root of our app (or apps/my_app_web in an umbrella app):

$ mix phx.gen.auth Accounts User users

An authentication system can be created in two different ways:
- Using Phoenix.LiveView (default)
- Using Phoenix.Controller only

Do you want to create a LiveView based authentication system? [Y/n] Y

The authentication generators support Phoenix LiveView, for enhanced UX, so we'll answer Y here. You may also answer n for a controller based authentication system.

Either approach will create an Accounts context with an Accounts.User schema module. The final argument is the plural version of the schema module, which is used for generating database table names and route paths. The mix phx.gen.auth generator is similar to mix phx.gen.html except it does not accept a list of additional fields to add to the schema, and it generates many more context functions.

Since this generator installed additional dependencies in mix.exs, let's fetch those:

$ mix deps.get

Now we need to verify the database connection details for the development and test environments in config/ so the migrator and tests can run properly. Then run the following to create the database:

$ mix ecto.setup

Let's run the tests to make sure our new authentication system works as expected.

$ mix test

And finally, let's start our Phoenix server and try it out.

$ mix phx.server

Developer responsibilities

Since Phoenix generates this code into your application instead of building these modules into Phoenix itself, you now have complete freedom to modify the authentication system, so it works best with your use case. The one caveat with using a generated authentication system is it will not be updated after it's been generated. Therefore, as improvements are made to the output of mix phx.gen.auth, it becomes your responsibility to determine if these changes need to be ported into your application. Security-related and other important improvements will be explicitly and clearly marked in the CHANGELOG.md file and upgrade notes.

Generated code

The following are notes about the generated authentication system.

Password hashing

The password hashing mechanism defaults to bcrypt for Unix systems and pbkdf2 for Windows systems. Both systems use the Comeonin interface.

The password hashing mechanism can be overridden with the --hashing-lib option. The following values are supported:

bcrypt - bcrypt_elixir
pbkdf2 - pbkdf2_elixir
argon2 - argon2_elixir

We recommend developers to consider using argon2, which is the most robust of all 3. The downside is that argon2 is quite CPU and memory intensive, and you will need more powerful instances to run your applications on.

For more information about choosing these libraries, see the Comeonin project.

Forbidding access

The generated code ships with an authentication module with a handful of plugs that fetch the current user, require authentication and so on. For instance, in an app named Demo which had mix phx.gen.auth Accounts User users run on it, you will find a module named DemoWeb.UserAuth with plugs such as:

fetch_current_user - fetches the current user information if available
require_authenticated_user - must be invoked after fetch_current_user and requires that a current user exists and is authenticated
redirect_if_user_is_authenticated - used for the few pages that must not be available to authenticated users

Confirmation

The generated functionality ships with an account confirmation mechanism, where users have to confirm their account, typically by email. However, the generated code does not forbid users from using the application if their accounts have not yet been confirmed. You can add this functionality by customizing the require_authenticated_user in the Auth module to check for the confirmed_at field (and any other property you desire).

Notifiers

The generated code is not integrated with any system to send SMSes or emails for confirming accounts, resetting passwords, etc. Instead, it simply logs a message to the terminal. It is your responsibility to integrate with the proper system after generation.

Note that if you generated your Phoenix project with mix phx.new, your project is configured to use Swoosh mailer by default. To view notifier emails during development with Swoosh, navigate to /dev/mailbox.

Tracking sessions

All sessions and tokens are tracked in a separate table. This allows you to track how many sessions are active for each account. You could even expose this information to users if desired.

Note that whenever the password changes (either via reset password or directly), all tokens are deleted, and the user has to log in again on all devices.

User Enumeration attacks

A user enumeration attack allows someone to check if an email is registered in the application. The generated authentication code does not attempt to protect from such checks. For instance, when you register an account, if the email is already registered, the code will notify the user the email is already registered.

If your application is sensitive to enumeration attacks, you need to implement your own workflows, which tends to be very different from most applications, as you need to carefully balance security and user experience.

Furthermore, if you are concerned about enumeration attacks, beware of timing attacks too. For example, registering a new account typically involves additional work (such as writing to the database, sending emails, etc) compared to when an account already exists. Someone could measure the time taken to execute those additional tasks to enumerate emails. This applies to all endpoints (registration, confirmation, password recovery, etc.) that may send email, in-app notifications, etc.

Case sensitiveness

The email lookup is made to be case-insensitive. Case-insensitive lookups are the default in MySQL and MSSQL. In SQLite3 we use COLLATE NOCASE in the column definition to support it. In PostgreSQL, we use the citext extension.

Note citext is part of PostgreSQL itself and is bundled with it in most operating systems and package managers. mix phx.gen.auth takes care of creating the extension and no extra work is necessary in the majority of cases. If by any chance your package manager splits citext into a separate package, you will get an error while migrating, and you can most likely solve it by installing the postgres-contrib package.

Concurrent tests

The generated tests run concurrently if you are using a database that supports concurrent tests, which is the case of PostgreSQL.

More about mix phx.gen.auth

Check out mix phx.gen.auth for more details, such as using a different password hashing library, customizing the web module namespace, generating binary id type, configuring the default options, and using custom table names.

Additional resources

The following links have more information regarding the motivation and design of the code this generates.

Berenice Medel's blog post on generating LiveViews for authentication (rather than conventional Controllers & Views) - Bringing Phoenix Authentication to Life
José Valim's blog post - An upcoming authentication solution for Phoenix
The original phx_gen_auth repo (for Phoenix 1.5 applications) - This is a great resource to see discussions around decisions that have been made in earlier versions of the project.
Original pull request on bare Phoenix app
Original design spec

Overview

Phoenix is a web development framework written in Elixir which implements the server-side Model View Controller (MVC) pattern. Many of its components and concepts will seem familiar to those of us with experience in other web frameworks like Ruby on Rails or Python's Django.

Phoenix provides the best of both worlds - high developer productivity and high application performance. It also has some interesting new twists like channels for implementing realtime features and pre-compiled templates for blazing speed.

If you are already familiar with Elixir, great! If not, there are a number of places to learn. The Elixir guides and the Elixir learning resources page are two great places to start.

The guides that you are currently looking at provide an overview of all parts that make Phoenix. Here is a rundown of what they provide:

Introduction - the guides you are currently reading. They will cover how to get your first application up and running

Guides - in-depth guides covering the main components in Phoenix and Phoenix applications

Authentication - in-depth guide covering how to use mix phx.gen.auth

Real-time components - in-depth guides covering Phoenix's built-in real-time components

Testing - in-depth guides about testing

Deployment - in-depth guides about deployment

How-to's - a collection of articles on how to achieve certain things with Phoenix

If you would prefer to read these guides as an EPUB, click here!

Note, these guides are not a step-by-step introduction to Phoenix. If you want a more structured approach to learning the framework, we have a large community and many books, courses, and screencasts available. See our community page for a complete list.

Let's get Phoenix installed.

Phoenix.Endpoint behaviour

Defines a Phoenix endpoint.

The endpoint is the boundary where all requests to your web application start. It is also the interface your application provides to the underlying web servers.

Overall, an endpoint has three responsibilities:

to provide a wrapper for starting and stopping the endpoint as part of a supervision tree

to define an initial plug pipeline for requests to pass through

to host web specific configuration for your application

Endpoints

An endpoint is simply a module defined with the help of Phoenix.Endpoint. If you have used the mix phx.new generator, an endpoint was automatically generated as part of your application:

defmodule YourAppWeb.Endpoint do
  use Phoenix.Endpoint, otp_app: :your_app

  # plug ...
  # plug ...

  plug YourApp.Router
end

Endpoints must be explicitly started as part of your application supervision tree. Endpoints are added by default to the supervision tree in generated applications. Endpoints can be added to the supervision tree as follows:

children = [
  YourAppWeb.Endpoint
]

Endpoint configuration

All endpoints are configured in your application environment. For example:

config :your_app, YourAppWeb.Endpoint,
  secret_key_base: "kjoy3o1zeidquwy1398juxzldjlksahdk3"

Endpoint configuration is split into two categories. Compile-time configuration means the configuration is read during compilation and changing it at runtime has no effect. The compile-time configuration is mostly related to error handling.

Runtime configuration, instead, is accessed during or after your application is started and can be read through the config/2 function:

YourAppWeb.Endpoint.config(:port)
YourAppWeb.Endpoint.config(:some_config, :default_value)

Compile-time configuration

Compile-time configuration may be set on config/dev.exs, config/prod.exs and so on, but has no effect on config/runtime.exs:

:code_reloader - when true, enables code reloading functionality. For the list of code reloader configuration options see Phoenix.CodeReloader.reload/1. Keep in mind code reloading is based on the file-system, therefore it is not possible to run two instances of the same app at the same time with code reloading in development, as they will race each other and only one will effectively recompile the files. In such cases, tweak your config files so code reloading is enabled in only one of the apps or set the MIX_BUILD environment variable to give them distinct build directories

:debug_errors - when true, uses Plug.Debugger functionality for debugging failures in the application. Recommended to be set to true only in development as it allows listing of the application source code during debugging. Defaults to false

:force_ssl - ensures no data is ever sent via HTTP, always redirecting to HTTPS. It expects a list of options which are forwarded to Plug.SSL. By default it sets the "strict-transport-security" header in HTTPS requests, forcing browsers to always use HTTPS. If an unsafe request (HTTP) is sent, it redirects to the HTTPS version using the :host specified in the :url configuration. To dynamically redirect to the host of the current request, set :host in the :force_ssl configuration to nil

Runtime configuration

The configuration below may be set on config/dev.exs, config/prod.exs and so on, as well as on config/runtime.exs. Typically, if you need to configure them with system environment variables, you set them in config/runtime.exs. These options may also be set when starting the endpoint in your supervision tree, such as {MyApp.Endpoint, options}.

:adapter - which webserver adapter to use for serving web requests. See the "Adapter configuration" section below

:cache_static_manifest - a path to a json manifest file that contains static files and their digested version. This is typically set to "priv/static/cache_manifest.json" which is the file automatically generated by mix phx.digest. It can be either: a string containing a file system path or a tuple containing the application name and the path within that application.

:cache_static_manifest_latest - a map of the static files pointing to their digest version. This is automatically loaded from cache_static_manifest on boot. However, if you have your own static handling mechanism, you may want to set this value explicitly. This is used by projects such as LiveView to detect if the client is running on the latest version of all assets.

:cache_manifest_skip_vsn - when true, skips the appended query string "?vsn=d" when generating paths to static assets. This query string is used by Plug.Static to set long expiry dates, therefore, you should set this option to true only if you are not using Plug.Static to serve assets, for example, if you are using a CDN. If you are setting this option, you should also consider passing --no-vsn to mix phx.digest. Defaults to false.

:check_origin - configure the default :check_origin setting for transports. See socket/3 for options. Defaults to true.

:secret_key_base - a secret key used as a base to generate secrets for encrypting and signing data. For example, cookies and tokens are signed by default, but they may also be encrypted if desired. Defaults to nil as it must be set per application

:server - when true, starts the web server when the endpoint supervision tree starts. Defaults to false. The mix phx.server task automatically sets this to true

:url - configuration for generating URLs throughout the app. Accepts the :host, :scheme, :path and :port options. All keys except :path can be changed at runtime. Defaults to:

[host: "localhost", path: "/"]

The :port option requires either an integer or string. The :host option requires a string.

The :scheme option accepts "http" and "https" values. Default value is inferred from top level :http or :https option. It is useful when hosting Phoenix behind a load balancer or reverse proxy and terminating SSL there.

The :path option can be used to override root path. Useful when hosting Phoenix behind a reverse proxy with URL rewrite rules

:static_url - configuration for generating URLs for static files. It will fallback to url if no option is provided. Accepts the same options as url

:watchers - a set of watchers to run alongside your server. It expects a list of tuples containing the executable and its arguments. Watchers are guaranteed to run in the application directory, but only when the server is enabled (unless :force_watchers configuration is set to true). For example, the watcher below will run the "watch" mode of the webpack build tool when the server starts. You can configure it to whatever build tool or command you want:

[
  node: [
    "node_modules/webpack/bin/webpack.js",
    "--mode",
    "development",
    "--watch",
    "--watch-options-stdin"
  ]
]

The :cd and :env options can be given at the end of the list to customize the watcher:

[node: [..., cd: "assets", env: [{"TAILWIND_MODE", "watch"}]]]

A watcher can also be a module-function-args tuple that will be invoked accordingly:

[another: {Mod, :fun, [arg1, arg2]}]

:force_watchers - when true, forces your watchers to start even when the :server option is set to false.

:live_reload - configuration for the live reload option. Configuration requires a :patterns option which should be a list of file patterns to watch. When these files change, it will trigger a reload.

live_reload: [
  url: "ws://localhost:4000",
  patterns: [
    ~r"priv/static/(?!uploads/).*(js|css|png|jpeg|jpg|gif|svg)$",
    ~r"lib/app_web/(live|views)/.*(ex)$",
    ~r"lib/app_web/templates/.*(eex)$"
  ]
]

:pubsub_server - the name of the pubsub server to use in channels and via the Endpoint broadcast functions. The PubSub server is typically started in your supervision tree.

:render_errors - responsible for rendering templates whenever there is a failure in the application. For example, if the application crashes with a 500 error during a HTML request, render("500.html", assigns) will be called in the view given to :render_errors. A :formats list can be provided to specify a module per format to handle error rendering. Example:

[formats: [html: MyApp.ErrorHTML], layout: false, log: :debug]

:log_access_url - log the access url once the server boots

Note that you can also store your own configurations in the Phoenix.Endpoint. For example, Phoenix LiveView expects its own configuration under the :live_view key. In such cases, you should consult the documentation of the respective projects.

Adapter configuration

Phoenix allows you to choose which webserver adapter to use. Newly generated applications created via the phx.new Mix task use the Bandit webserver via the Bandit.PhoenixAdapter adapter. If not otherwise specified via the adapter option Phoenix will fall back to the Phoenix.Endpoint.Cowboy2Adapter for backwards compatibility with applications generated prior to Phoenix 1.7.8.

Both adapters can be configured in a similar manner using the following two top-level options:

:http - the configuration for the HTTP server. It accepts all options as defined by either Bandit or Plug.Cowboy depending on your choice of adapter. Defaults to false

:https - the configuration for the HTTPS server. It accepts all options as defined by either Bandit or Plug.Cowboy depending on your choice of adapter. Defaults to false

In addition, the connection draining can be configured for the Cowboy webserver via the following top-level option (this is not required for Bandit as it has connection draining built-in):

:drainer - a drainer process waits for any on-going request to finish during application shutdown. It accepts the :shutdown and :check_interval options as defined by Plug.Cowboy.Drainer. Note the draining does not terminate any existing connection, it simply waits for them to finish. Socket connections run their own drainer before this one is invoked. That's because sockets are stateful and can be gracefully notified, which allows us to stagger them over a longer period of time. See the documentation for socket/3 for more information

Endpoint API

In the previous section, we have used the config/2 function that is automatically generated in your endpoint. Here's a list of all the functions that are automatically defined in your endpoint:

for handling paths and URLs: struct_url/0, url/0, path/1, static_url/0,static_path/1, and static_integrity/1

for gathering runtime information about the address and port the endpoint is running on: server_info/1

for broadcasting to channels: broadcast/3, broadcast!/3, broadcast_from/4, broadcast_from!/4, local_broadcast/3, and local_broadcast_from/4

for configuration: start_link/1, config/2, and config_change/2

as required by the Plug behaviour: Plug.init/1 and Plug.call/2

Summary

Types

event()

msg()

topic()

Callbacks

broadcast(topic, event, msg)

Broadcasts a msg as event in the given topic to all nodes.

broadcast!(topic, event, msg)

Broadcasts a msg as event in the given topic to all nodes.

broadcast_from(from, topic, event, msg)

Broadcasts a msg from the given from as event in the given topic to all nodes.

broadcast_from!(from, topic, event, msg)

Broadcasts a msg from the given from as event in the given topic to all nodes.

config key, default

Access the endpoint configuration given by key.

config_change(changed, removed)

Reload the endpoint configuration on application upgrades.

host()

Returns the host from the :url configuration.

local_broadcast(topic, event, msg)

Broadcasts a msg as event in the given topic within the current node.

local_broadcast_from(from, topic, event, msg)

Broadcasts a msg from the given from as event in the given topic within the current node.

path(path)

Generates the path information when routing to this endpoint.

script_name()

Returns the script name from the :url configuration.

server_info(scheme)

Returns the address and port that the server is running on

start_link(keyword)

Starts the endpoint supervision tree.

static_integrity(path)

Generates an integrity hash to a static file in priv/static.

static_lookup(path)

Generates a two item tuple containing the static_path and static_integrity.

static_path(path)

Generates a route to a static file in priv/static.

static_url()

Generates the static URL without any path information.

struct_url()

Generates the endpoint base URL, but as a URI struct.

subscribe(topic, opts)

Subscribes the caller to the given topic.

unsubscribe(topic)

Unsubscribes the caller from the given topic.

url()

Generates the endpoint base URL without any path information.

Functions

server?(otp_app, endpoint)

Checks if Endpoint's web server has been configured to start.

socket(path, module, opts \\ [])

Defines a websocket/longpoll mount-point for a socket.

Types

event()

@type event() :: String.t()

msg()

@type msg() :: map() | {:binary, binary()}

topic()

@type topic() :: String.t()

Callbacks

broadcast(topic, event, msg)

@callback broadcast(topic(), event(), msg()) :: :ok | {:error, term()}

Broadcasts a msg as event in the given topic to all nodes.

broadcast!(topic, event, msg)

@callback broadcast!(topic(), event(), msg()) :: :ok

Broadcasts a msg as event in the given topic to all nodes.

Raises in case of failures.

broadcast_from(from, topic, event, msg)

@callback broadcast_from(from :: pid(), topic(), event(), msg()) :: :ok | {:error, term()}

Broadcasts a msg from the given from as event in the given topic to all nodes.

broadcast_from!(from, topic, event, msg)

@callback broadcast_from!(from :: pid(), topic(), event(), msg()) :: :ok

Broadcasts a msg from the given from as event in the given topic to all nodes.

Raises in case of failures.

config key, default

@callback config(key :: atom(), default :: term()) :: term()

Access the endpoint configuration given by key.

config_change(changed, removed)

@callback config_change(changed :: term(), removed :: term()) :: term()

Reload the endpoint configuration on application upgrades.

host()

@callback host() :: String.t()

Returns the host from the :url configuration.

local_broadcast(topic, event, msg)

@callback local_broadcast(topic(), event(), msg()) :: :ok

Broadcasts a msg as event in the given topic within the current node.

local_broadcast_from(from, topic, event, msg)

@callback local_broadcast_from(from :: pid(), topic(), event(), msg()) :: :ok

Broadcasts a msg from the given from as event in the given topic within the current node.

path(path)

@callback path(path :: String.t()) :: String.t()

Generates the path information when routing to this endpoint.

script_name()

@callback script_name() :: [String.t()]

Returns the script name from the :url configuration.

server_info(scheme)

@callback server_info(Plug.Conn.scheme()) ::
  {:ok,
   {:inet.ip_address(), :inet.port_number()} | :inet.returned_non_ip_address()}
  | {:error, term()}

Returns the address and port that the server is running on

start_link(keyword)

@callback start_link(keyword()) :: Supervisor.on_start()

Starts the endpoint supervision tree.

Starts endpoint's configuration cache and possibly the servers for handling requests.

static_integrity(path)

@callback static_integrity(path :: String.t()) :: String.t() | nil

Generates an integrity hash to a static file in priv/static.

static_lookup(path)

@callback static_lookup(path :: String.t()) ::
  {String.t(), String.t()} | {String.t(), nil}

Generates a two item tuple containing the static_path and static_integrity.

static_path(path)

@callback static_path(path :: String.t()) :: String.t()

Generates a route to a static file in priv/static.

static_url()

@callback static_url() :: String.t()

Generates the static URL without any path information.

struct_url()

@callback struct_url() :: URI.t()

Generates the endpoint base URL, but as a URI struct.

subscribe(topic, opts)

@callback subscribe(topic(), opts :: Keyword.t()) :: :ok | {:error, term()}

Subscribes the caller to the given topic.

See Phoenix.PubSub.subscribe/3 for options.

unsubscribe(topic)

@callback unsubscribe(topic()) :: :ok | {:error, term()}

Unsubscribes the caller from the given topic.

url()

@callback url() :: String.t()

Generates the endpoint base URL without any path information.

Functions

server?(otp_app, endpoint)

Checks if Endpoint's web server has been configured to start.

otp_app - The OTP app running the endpoint, for example :my_app
endpoint - The endpoint module, for example MyAppWeb.Endpoint

Examples

iex> Phoenix.Endpoint.server?(:my_app, MyAppWeb.Endpoint)
true

socket(path, module, opts \\ [])

(macro)

Defines a websocket/longpoll mount-point for a socket.

It expects a path, a socket module, and a set of options. The socket module is typically defined with Phoenix.Socket.

Both websocket and longpolling connections are supported out of the box.

Options

:websocket - controls the websocket configuration. Defaults to true. May be false or a keyword list of options. See "Common configuration" and "WebSocket configuration" for the whole list

:longpoll - controls the longpoll configuration. Defaults to false. May be true or a keyword list of options. See "Common configuration" and "Longpoll configuration" for the whole list

:drainer - a keyword list or a custom MFA function returning a keyword list, for example:

{MyAppWeb.Socket, :drainer_configuration, []}

configuring how to drain sockets on application shutdown. The goal is to notify all channels (and LiveViews) clients to reconnect. The supported options are:

:batch_size - How many clients to notify at once in a given batch. Defaults to 10000.
:batch_interval - The amount of time in milliseconds given for a batch to terminate. Defaults to 2000ms.
:shutdown - The maximum amount of time in milliseconds allowed to drain all batches. Defaults to 30000ms.
:log - the log level for drain actions. Defaults the :log option passed to use Phoenix.Socket or :info. Set it to false to disable logging.

For example, if you have 150k connections, the default values will split them into 15 batches of 10k connections. Each batch takes 2000ms before the next batch starts. In this case, we will do everything right under the maximum shutdown time of 30000ms. Therefore, as you increase the number of connections, remember to adjust the shutdown accordingly. Finally, after the socket drainer runs, the lower level HTTP/HTTPS connection drainer will still run, and apply to all connections. Set it to false to disable draining.

You can also pass the options below on use Phoenix.Socket. The values specified here override the value in use Phoenix.Socket.

Examples

socket "/ws", MyApp.UserSocket

socket "/ws/admin", MyApp.AdminUserSocket,
  longpoll: true,
  websocket: [compress: true]

Path params

It is possible to include variables in the path, these will be available in the params that are passed to the socket.

socket "/ws/:user_id", MyApp.UserSocket,
  websocket: [path: "/project/:project_id"]

Common configuration

The configuration below can be given to both :websocket and :longpoll keys:

:path - the path to use for the transport. Will default to the transport name ("/websocket" or "/longpoll")

:serializer - a list of serializers for messages. See Phoenix.Socket for more information

:transport_log - if the transport layer itself should log and, if so, the level

:check_origin - if the transport should check the origin of requests when the origin header is present. May be true, false, a list of hosts that are allowed, or a function provided as MFA tuple. Defaults to :check_origin setting at endpoint configuration.

If true, the header is checked against :host in YourAppWeb.Endpoint.config(:url)[:host].

If false and you do not validate the session in your socket, your app is vulnerable to Cross-Site WebSocket Hijacking (CSWSH) attacks. Only use in development, when the host is truly unknown or when serving clients that do not send the origin header, such as mobile apps.

You can also specify a list of explicitly allowed origins. Wildcards are supported.

check_origin: [
  "https://example.com",
  "//another.com:888",
  "//*.other.com"
]

Or to accept any origin matching the request connection's host, port, and scheme:

check_origin: :conn

Or a custom MFA function:

check_origin: {MyAppWeb.Auth, :my_check_origin?, []}

The MFA is invoked with the request %URI{} as the first argument, followed by arguments in the MFA list, and must return a boolean.

:code_reloader - enable or disable the code reloader. Defaults to your endpoint configuration

:connect_info - a list of keys that represent data to be copied from the transport to be made available in the user socket connect/3 callback. See the "Connect info" subsection for valid keys

Connect info

The valid keys are:

:peer_data - the result of Plug.Conn.get_peer_data/1

:trace_context_headers - a list of all trace context headers. Supported headers are defined by the W3C Trace Context Specification. These headers are necessary for libraries such as OpenTelemetry to extract trace propagation information to know this request is part of a larger trace in progress.

:x_headers - all request headers that have an "x-" prefix

:uri - a %URI{} with information from the conn

:user_agent - the value of the "user-agent" request header

{:session, session_config} - the session information from Plug.Conn. The session_config is typically an exact copy of the arguments given to Plug.Session. In order to validate the session, the "_csrf_token" must be given as request parameter when connecting the socket with the value of URI.encode_www_form(Plug.CSRFProtection.get_csrf_token()). The CSRF token request parameter can be modified via the :csrf_token_key option.

Additionally, session_config may be a MFA, such as {MyAppWeb.Auth, :get_session_config, []}, to allow loading config in runtime.

Arbitrary keywords may also appear following the above valid keys, which is useful for passing custom connection information to the socket.

For example:

  socket "/socket", AppWeb.UserSocket,
      websocket: [
        connect_info: [:peer_data, :trace_context_headers, :x_headers, :uri, session: [store: :cookie]]
      ]

With arbitrary keywords:

  socket "/socket", AppWeb.UserSocket,
      websocket: [
        connect_info: [:uri, custom_value: "abcdef"]
      ]

Where are my headers?

Phoenix only gives you limited access to the connection headers for security reasons. WebSockets are cross-domain, which means that, when a user "John Doe" visits a malicious website, the malicious website can open up a WebSocket connection to your application, and the browser will gladly submit John Doe's authentication/cookie information. If you were to accept this information as is, the malicious website would have full control of a WebSocket connection to your application, authenticated on John Doe's behalf.

To safe-guard your application, Phoenix limits and validates the connection information your socket can access. This means your application is safe from these attacks, but you can't access cookies and other headers in your socket. You may access the session stored in the connection via the :connect_info option, provided you also pass a csrf token when connecting over WebSocket.

Websocket configuration

The following configuration applies only to :websocket.

:timeout - the timeout for keeping websocket connections open after it last received data, defaults to 60_000ms

:max_frame_size - the maximum allowed frame size in bytes, defaults to "infinity"

:fullsweep_after - the maximum number of garbage collections before forcing a fullsweep for the socket process. You can set it to 0 to force more frequent cleanups of your websocket transport processes. Setting this option requires Erlang/OTP 24

:compress - whether to enable per message compression on all data frames, defaults to false

:subprotocols - a list of supported websocket subprotocols. Used for handshake Sec-WebSocket-Protocol response header, defaults to nil.

For example:

subprotocols: ["sip", "mqtt"]

:error_handler - custom error handler for connection errors. If Phoenix.Socket.connect/3 returns an {:error, reason} tuple, the error handler will be called with the error reason. For WebSockets, the error handler must be a MFA tuple that receives a Plug.Conn, the error reason, and returns a Plug.Conn with a response. For example:

socket "/socket", MySocket,
    websocket: [
      error_handler: {MySocket, :handle_error, []}
    ]

and a {:error, :rate_limit} return may be handled on MySocket as:

def handle_error(conn, :rate_limit), do: Plug.Conn.send_resp(conn, 429, "Too many requests")

Longpoll configuration

The following configuration applies only to :longpoll:

:window_ms - how long the client can wait for new messages in its poll request in milliseconds (ms). Defaults to 10_000.

:pubsub_timeout_ms - how long a request can wait for the pubsub layer to respond in milliseconds (ms). Defaults to 2000.

:crypto - options for verifying and signing the token, accepted by Phoenix.Token. By default tokens are valid for 2 weeks

Routing

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the introductory guides and got a Phoenix application up and running.

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the Request life-cycle guide.

Routers are the main hubs of Phoenix applications. They match HTTP requests to controller actions, wire up real-time channel handlers, and define a series of pipeline transformations scoped to a set of routes.

The router file that Phoenix generates, lib/hello_web/router.ex, will look something like this one:

defmodule HelloWeb.Router do
  use HelloWeb, :router

  pipeline :browser do
    plug :accepts, ["html"]
    plug :fetch_session
    plug :fetch_live_flash
    plug :put_root_layout, html: {HelloWeb.Layouts, :root}
    plug :protect_from_forgery
    plug :put_secure_browser_headers
  end

  pipeline :api do
    plug :accepts, ["json"]
  end

  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    get "/", PageController, :home
  end

  # Other scopes may use custom stacks.
  # scope "/api", HelloWeb do
  #   pipe_through :api
  # end
  # ...
end

Both the router and controller module names will be prefixed with the name you gave your application suffixed with Web.

The first line of this module, use HelloWeb, :router, simply makes Phoenix router functions available in our particular router.

Scopes have their own section in this guide, so we won't spend time on the scope "/", HelloWeb do block here. The pipe_through :browser line will get a full treatment in the "Pipelines" section of this guide. For now, you only need to know that pipelines allow a set of plugs to be applied to different sets of routes.

Inside the scope block, however, we have our first actual route:

get "/", PageController, :home

get is a Phoenix macro that corresponds to the HTTP verb GET. Similar macros exist for other HTTP verbs, including POST, PUT, PATCH, DELETE, OPTIONS, CONNECT, TRACE, and HEAD.

Why the macros?

Phoenix does its best to keep the usage of macros low. You may have noticed, however, that the Phoenix.Router relies heavily on macros. Why is that?

We use get, post, put, and delete to define your routes. We use macros for two purposes:

They define the routing engine, used on every request, to choose which controller to dispatch the request to. Thanks to macros, Phoenix compiles all of your routes to a huge case-statement with pattern matching rules, which is heavily optimized by the Erlang VM

For each route you define, we also define metadata to implement Phoenix.VerifiedRoutes. As we will soon learn, verified routes allow us to reference any route as if it were a plain looking string, except that it is verified by the compiler to be valid (making it much harder to ship broken links, forms, mails, etc to production)

In other words, the router relies on macros to build applications that are faster and safer. Also remember that macros in Elixir are compile-time only, which gives plenty of stability after the code is compiled. As we will learn next, Phoenix also provides introspection for all defined routes via mix phx.routes.

Examining routes

Phoenix provides an excellent tool for investigating routes in an application: mix phx.routes.

Let's see how this works. Go to the root of a newly-generated Phoenix application and run mix phx.routes. You should see something like the following, generated with all routes you currently have:

$ mix phx.routes
GET  /  HelloWeb.PageController :home
...

The route above tells us that any HTTP GET request for the root of the application will be handled by the home action of the HelloWeb.PageController.

Resources

The router supports other macros besides those for HTTP verbs like get, post, and put. The most important among them is resources. Let's add a resource to our lib/hello_web/router.ex file like this:

scope "/", HelloWeb do
  pipe_through :browser

  get "/", PageController, :home
  resources "/users", UserController
  ...
end

For now it doesn't matter that we don't actually have a HelloWeb.UserController.

Run mix phx.routes once again at the root of your project. You should see something like the following:

...
GET     /users           HelloWeb.UserController :index
GET     /users/:id/edit  HelloWeb.UserController :edit
GET     /users/new       HelloWeb.UserController :new
GET     /users/:id       HelloWeb.UserController :show
POST    /users           HelloWeb.UserController :create
PATCH   /users/:id       HelloWeb.UserController :update
PUT     /users/:id       HelloWeb.UserController :update
DELETE  /users/:id       HelloWeb.UserController :delete
...

This is the standard matrix of HTTP verbs, paths, and controller actions. For a while, this was known as RESTful routes, but most consider this a misnomer nowadays. Let's look at them individually.

A GET request to /users will invoke the index action to show all the users.
A GET request to /users/:id/edit will invoke the edit action with an ID to retrieve an individual user from the data store and present the information in a form for editing.
A GET request to /users/new will invoke the new action to present a form for creating a new user.
A GET request to /users/:id will invoke the show action with an id to show an individual user identified by that ID.
A POST request to /users will invoke the create action to save a new user to the data store.
A PATCH request to /users/:id will invoke the update action with an ID to save the updated user to the data store.
A PUT request to /users/:id will also invoke the update action with an ID to save the updated user to the data store.
A DELETE request to /users/:id will invoke the delete action with an ID to remove the individual user from the data store.

If we don't need all these routes, we can be selective using the :only and :except options to filter specific actions.

Let's say we have a read-only posts resource. We could define it like this:

resources "/posts", PostController, only: [:index, :show]

Running mix phx.routes shows that we now only have the routes to the index and show actions defined.

GET     /posts      HelloWeb.PostController :index
GET     /posts/:id  HelloWeb.PostController :show

Similarly, if we have a comments resource, and we don't want to provide a route to delete one, we could define a route like this.

resources "/comments", CommentController, except: [:delete]

Running mix phx.routes now shows that we have all the routes except the DELETE request to the delete action.

GET    /comments           HelloWeb.CommentController :index
GET    /comments/:id/edit  HelloWeb.CommentController :edit
GET    /comments/new       HelloWeb.CommentController :new
GET    /comments/:id       HelloWeb.CommentController :show
POST   /comments           HelloWeb.CommentController :create
PATCH  /comments/:id       HelloWeb.CommentController :update
PUT    /comments/:id       HelloWeb.CommentController :update

The Phoenix.Router.resources/4 macro describes additional options for customizing resource routes.

Verified Routes

Phoenix includes Phoenix.VerifiedRoutes module which provides compile-time checks of router paths against your router by using the ~p sigil. For example, you can write paths in controllers, tests, and templates and the compiler will make sure those actually match routes defined in your router.

Let's see it in action. Run iex -S mix at the root of the project. We'll define a throwaway example module that builds a couple ~p route paths.

iex> defmodule RouteExample do
...>   use HelloWeb, :verified_routes
...>
...>   def example do
...>     ~p"/comments"
...>     ~p"/unknown/123"
...>   end
...> end
warning: no route path for HelloWeb.Router matches "/unknown/123"
  iex:5: RouteExample.example/0

{:module, RouteExample, ...}
iex>

Notice how the first call to an existing route, ~p"/comments" gave no warning, but a bad route path ~p"/unknown/123" produced a compiler warning, just as it should. This is significant because it allows us to write otherwise hard-coded paths in our application and the compiler will let us know whenever we write a bad route or change our routing structure.

Phoenix projects are set up out of the box to allow use of verified routes throughout your web layer, including tests. For example in your templates you can render ~p links:

<.link href={~p"/"}>Welcome Page!</.link>
<.link href={~p"/comments"}>View Comments</.link>

Or in a controller, issue a redirect:

redirect(conn, to: ~p"/comments/#{comment}")

Using ~p for route paths ensures our application paths and URLs stay up to date with the router definitions. The compiler will catch bugs for us, and let us know when we change routes that are referenced elsewhere in our application.

More on verified routes

What about paths with query strings? You can either add query string key values directly, or provide a dictionary of key-value pairs, for example:

~p"/users/17?admin=true&active=false"
"/users/17?admin=true&active=false"

~p"/users/17?#{[admin: true]}"
"/users/17?admin=true"

What if we need a full URL instead of a path? Just wrap your path with a call to Phoenix.VerifiedRoutes.url/1, which is imported everywhere that ~p is available:

url(~p"/users")
"http://localhost:4000/users"

The url calls will get the host, port, proxy port, and SSL information needed to construct the full URL from the configuration parameters set for each environment. We'll talk about configuration in more detail in its own guide. For now, you can take a look at config/dev.exs file in your own project to see those values.

Nested resources

It is also possible to nest resources in a Phoenix router. Let's say we also have a posts resource that has a many-to-one relationship with users. That is to say, a user can create many posts, and an individual post belongs to only one user. We can represent that by adding a nested route in lib/hello_web/router.ex like this:

resources "/users", UserController do
  resources "/posts", PostController
end

When we run mix phx.routes now, in addition to the routes we saw for users above, we get the following set of routes:

...
GET     /users/:user_id/posts           HelloWeb.PostController :index
GET     /users/:user_id/posts/:id/edit  HelloWeb.PostController :edit
GET     /users/:user_id/posts/new       HelloWeb.PostController :new
GET     /users/:user_id/posts/:id       HelloWeb.PostController :show
POST    /users/:user_id/posts           HelloWeb.PostController :create
PATCH   /users/:user_id/posts/:id       HelloWeb.PostController :update
PUT     /users/:user_id/posts/:id       HelloWeb.PostController :update
DELETE  /users/:user_id/posts/:id       HelloWeb.PostController :delete
...

We see that each of these routes scopes the posts to a user ID. For the first one, we will invoke PostController's index action, but we will pass in a user_id. This implies that we would display all the posts for that individual user only. The same scoping applies for all these routes.

When building paths for nested routes, we will need to interpolate the IDs where they belong in route definition. For the following show route, 42 is the user_id, and 17 is the post_id.

user_id = 42
post_id = 17
~p"/users/#{user_id}/posts/#{post_id}"
"/users/42/posts/17"

Verified routes also support the Phoenix.Param protocol, but we don't need to concern ourselves with Elixir protocols just yet. Just know that once we start building our application with structs like %User{} and %Post{}, we'll be able to interpolate those data structures directly into our ~p paths and Phoenix will pluck out the correct fields to use in the route.

~p"/users/#{user}/posts/#{post}"
"/users/42/posts/17"

Notice how we didn't need to interpolate user.id or post.id? This is particularly nice if we decide later we want to make our URLs a little nicer and start using slugs instead. We don't need to change any of our ~p's!

Scoped routes

Scopes are a way to group routes under a common path prefix and scoped set of plugs. We might want to do this for admin functionality, APIs, and especially for versioned APIs. Let's say we have user-generated reviews on a site, and that those reviews first need to be approved by an administrator. The semantics of these resources are quite different, and they might not share the same controller. Scopes enable us to segregate these routes.

The paths to the user-facing reviews would look like a standard resource.

/reviews
/reviews/1234
/reviews/1234/edit
...

The administration review paths can be prefixed with /admin.

/admin/reviews
/admin/reviews/1234
/admin/reviews/1234/edit
...

We accomplish this with a scoped route that sets a path option to /admin like this one. We can nest this scope inside another scope, but instead, let's set it by itself at the root, by adding to lib/hello_web/router.ex the following:

scope "/admin", HelloWeb.Admin do
  pipe_through :browser

  resources "/reviews", ReviewController
end

We define a new scope where all routes are prefixed with /admin and all controllers are under the HelloWeb.Admin namespace.

Running mix phx.routes again, in addition to the previous set of routes we get the following:

...
GET     /admin/reviews           HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :index
GET     /admin/reviews/:id/edit  HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :edit
GET     /admin/reviews/new       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :new
GET     /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :show
POST    /admin/reviews           HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :create
PATCH   /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :update
PUT     /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :update
DELETE  /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :delete
...

This looks good, but there is a problem here. Remember that we wanted both user-facing review routes /reviews and the admin ones /admin/reviews. If we now include the user-facing reviews in our router under the root scope like this:

scope "/", HelloWeb do
  pipe_through :browser

  ...
  resources "/reviews", ReviewController
end

scope "/admin", HelloWeb.Admin do
  pipe_through :browser

  resources "/reviews", ReviewController
end

and we run mix phx.routes, we get output for each scoped route:

...
GET     /reviews                 HelloWeb.ReviewController :index
GET     /reviews/:id/edit        HelloWeb.ReviewController :edit
GET     /reviews/new             HelloWeb.ReviewController :new
GET     /reviews/:id             HelloWeb.ReviewController :show
POST    /reviews                 HelloWeb.ReviewController :create
PATCH   /reviews/:id             HelloWeb.ReviewController :update
PUT     /reviews/:id             HelloWeb.ReviewController :update
DELETE  /reviews/:id             HelloWeb.ReviewController :delete
...
GET     /admin/reviews           HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :index
GET     /admin/reviews/:id/edit  HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :edit
GET     /admin/reviews/new       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :new
GET     /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :show
POST    /admin/reviews           HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :create
PATCH   /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :update
PUT     /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :update
DELETE  /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :delete

What if we had a number of resources that were all handled by admins? We could put all of them inside the same scope like this:

scope "/admin", HelloWeb.Admin do
  pipe_through :browser

  resources "/images",  ImageController
  resources "/reviews", ReviewController
  resources "/users",   UserController
end

Here's what mix phx.routes tells us:

...
GET     /admin/images            HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :index
GET     /admin/images/:id/edit   HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :edit
GET     /admin/images/new        HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :new
GET     /admin/images/:id        HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :show
POST    /admin/images            HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :create
PATCH   /admin/images/:id        HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :update
PUT     /admin/images/:id        HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :update
DELETE  /admin/images/:id        HelloWeb.Admin.ImageController :delete
GET     /admin/reviews           HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :index
GET     /admin/reviews/:id/edit  HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :edit
GET     /admin/reviews/new       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :new
GET     /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :show
POST    /admin/reviews           HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :create
PATCH   /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :update
PUT     /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :update
DELETE  /admin/reviews/:id       HelloWeb.Admin.ReviewController :delete
GET     /admin/users             HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :index
GET     /admin/users/:id/edit    HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :edit
GET     /admin/users/new         HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :new
GET     /admin/users/:id         HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :show
POST    /admin/users             HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :create
PATCH   /admin/users/:id         HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :update
PUT     /admin/users/:id         HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :update
DELETE  /admin/users/:id         HelloWeb.Admin.UserController :delete

This is great, exactly what we want. Note how every route and controller is properly namespaced.

Scopes can also be arbitrarily nested, but you should do it carefully as nesting can sometimes make our code confusing and less clear. With that said, suppose that we had a versioned API with resources defined for images, reviews, and users. Then technically, we could set up routes for the versioned API like this:

scope "/api", HelloWeb.Api, as: :api do
  pipe_through :api

  scope "/v1", V1, as: :v1 do
    resources "/images",  ImageController
    resources "/reviews", ReviewController
    resources "/users",   UserController
  end
end

You can run mix phx.routes to see how these definitions will look like.

Interestingly, we can use multiple scopes with the same path as long as we are careful not to duplicate routes. The following router is perfectly fine with two scopes defined for the same path:

defmodule HelloWeb.Router do
  use Phoenix.Router
  ...
  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    resources "/users", UserController
  end

  scope "/", AnotherAppWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    resources "/posts", PostController
  end
  ...
end

If we do duplicate a route — which means two routes having the same path — we'll get this familiar warning:

warning: this clause cannot match because a previous clause at line 16 always matches

Pipelines

We have come quite a long way in this guide without talking about one of the first lines we saw in the router: pipe_through :browser. It's time to fix that.

Pipelines are a series of plugs that can be attached to specific scopes. If you are not familiar with plugs, we have an in-depth guide about them.

Routes are defined inside scopes and scopes may pipe through multiple pipelines. Once a route matches, Phoenix invokes all plugs defined in all pipelines associated to that route. For example, accessing / will pipe through the :browser pipeline, consequently invoking all of its plugs.

Phoenix defines two pipelines by default, :browser and :api, which can be used for a number of common tasks. In turn we can customize them as well as create new pipelines to meet our needs.

The :browser and :api pipelines

As their names suggest, the :browser pipeline prepares for routes which render requests for a browser, and the :api pipeline prepares for routes which produce data for an API.

The :browser pipeline has six plugs: The plug :accepts, ["html"] defines the accepted request format or formats. :fetch_session, which, naturally, fetches the session data and makes it available in the connection. :fetch_live_flash, which fetches any flash messages from LiveView and merges them with the controller flash messages. Then, the plug :put_root_layout will store the root layout for rendering purposes. Later :protect_from_forgery and :put_secure_browser_headers, protects form posts from cross-site forgery.

Currently, the :api pipeline only defines plug :accepts, ["json"].

The router invokes a pipeline on a route defined within a scope. Routes outside of a scope have no pipelines. Although the use of nested scopes is discouraged (see above the versioned API example), if we call pipe_through within a nested scope, the router will invoke all pipe_through's from parent scopes, followed by the nested one.

Those are a lot of words bunched up together. Let's take a look at some examples to untangle their meaning.

Here's another look at the router from a newly generated Phoenix application, this time with the /api scope uncommented back in and a route added.

defmodule HelloWeb.Router do
  use HelloWeb, :router

  pipeline :browser do
    plug :accepts, ["html"]
    plug :fetch_session
    plug :fetch_live_flash
    plug :put_root_layout, html: {HelloWeb.Layouts, :root}
    plug :protect_from_forgery
    plug :put_secure_browser_headers
  end

  pipeline :api do
    plug :accepts, ["json"]
  end

  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :browser

    get "/", PageController, :home
  end

  # Other scopes may use custom stacks.
  scope "/api", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :api

    resources "/reviews", ReviewController
  end
  # ...
end

When the server accepts a request, the request will always first pass through the plugs in our endpoint, after which it will attempt to match on the path and HTTP verb.

Let's say that the request matches our first route: a GET to /. The router will first pipe that request through the :browser pipeline - which will fetch the session data, fetch the flash, and execute forgery protection - before it dispatches the request to PageController's home action.

Conversely, suppose the request matches any of the routes defined by the resources/2 macro. In that case, the router will pipe it through the :api pipeline — which currently only performs content negotiation — before it dispatches further to the correct action of the HelloWeb.ReviewController.

If no route matches, no pipeline is invoked and a 404 error is raised.

Creating new pipelines

Phoenix allows us to create our own custom pipelines anywhere in the router. To do so, we call the pipeline/2 macro with these arguments: an atom for the name of our new pipeline and a block with all the plugs we want in it.

defmodule HelloWeb.Router do
  use HelloWeb, :router

  pipeline :browser do
    plug :accepts, ["html"]
    plug :fetch_session
    plug :fetch_live_flash
    plug :put_root_layout, html: {HelloWeb.Layouts, :root}
    plug :protect_from_forgery
    plug :put_secure_browser_headers
  end

  pipeline :auth do
    plug HelloWeb.Authentication
  end

  scope "/reviews", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through [:browser, :auth]

    resources "/", ReviewController
  end
end

The above assumes there is a plug called HelloWeb.Authentication that performs authentication and is now part of the :auth pipeline.

Note that pipelines themselves are plugs, so we can plug a pipeline inside another pipeline. For example, we could rewrite the auth pipeline above to automatically invoke browser, simplifying the downstream pipeline call:

  pipeline :auth do
    plug :browser
    plug :ensure_authenticated_user
    plug :ensure_user_owns_review
  end

  scope "/reviews", HelloWeb do
    pipe_through :auth

    resources "/", ReviewController
  end

How to organize my routes?

In Phoenix, we tend to define several pipelines, that provide specific functionality. For example, the :browser and :api pipelines are meant to be accessed by specific clients, browsers and http clients respectively.

Perhaps more importantly, it is also very common to define pipelines specific to authentication and authorization. For example, you might have a pipeline that requires all users are authenticated. Another pipeline may enforce only admin users can access certain routes.

Once your pipelines are defined, you reuse the pipelines in the desired scopes, grouping your routes around their pipelines. For example, going back to our reviews example. Let's say anyone can read a review, but only authenticated users can create them. Your routes could look like this:

pipeline :browser do
  ...
end

pipeline :auth do
  plug HelloWeb.Authentication
end

scope "/" do
  pipe_through [:browser]

  get "/reviews", PostController, :index
  get "/reviews/:id", PostController, :show
end

scope "/" do
  pipe_through [:browser, :auth]

  get "/reviews/new", PostController, :new
  post "/reviews", PostController, :create
end

Note in the above how the routes are split across different scopes. While the separation can be confusing at first, it has one big upside: it is very easy to inspect your routes and see all routes that, for example, require authentication and which ones do not. This helps with auditing and making sure your routes have the proper scope.

You can create as few or as many scopes as you want. Because pipelines are reusable across scopes, they help encapsulate common functionality and you can compose them as necessary on each scope you define.

Forward

The Phoenix.Router.forward/4 macro can be used to send all requests that start with a particular path to a particular plug. Let's say we have a part of our system that is responsible (it could even be a separate application or library) for running jobs in the background, it could have its own web interface for checking the status of the jobs. We can forward to this admin interface using:

defmodule HelloWeb.Router do
  use HelloWeb, :router

  ...

  scope "/", HelloWeb do
    ...
  end

  forward "/jobs", BackgroundJob.Plug
end

This means that all routes starting with /jobs will be sent to the HelloWeb.BackgroundJob.Plug module. Inside the plug, you can match on subroutes, such as /pending and /active that shows the status of certain jobs.

We can even mix the forward/4 macro with pipelines. If we wanted to ensure that the user was authenticated and was an administrator in order to see the jobs page, we could use the following in our router.

defmodule HelloWeb.Router do
  use HelloWeb, :router

  ...

  scope "/" do
    pipe_through [:authenticate_user, :ensure_admin]
    forward "/jobs", BackgroundJob.Plug
  end
end

This means the plugs in the authenticate_user and ensure_admin pipelines will be called before the BackgroundJob.Plug allowing them to send an appropriate response and halt the request accordingly.

The opts that are received in the init/1 callback of the Module Plug can be passed as a third argument. For example, maybe the background job lets you set the name of your application to be displayed on the page. This could be passed with:

forward "/jobs", BackgroundJob.Plug, name: "Hello Phoenix"

There is a fourth router_opts argument that can be passed. These options are outlined in the Phoenix.Router.scope/2 documentation.

BackgroundJob.Plug can be implemented as any Module Plug discussed in the Plug guide. Note though it is not advised to forward to another Phoenix endpoint. This is because plugs defined by your app and the forwarded endpoint would be invoked twice, which may lead to errors.

Summary

Routing is a big topic, and we have covered a lot of ground here. The important points to take away from this guide are:

Routes which begin with an HTTP verb name expand to a single clause of the match function.
Routes declared with resources expand to 8 clauses of the match function.
Resources may restrict the number of match function clauses by using the only: or except: options.
Any of these routes may be nested.
Any of these routes may be scoped to a given path.
Using verified routes with ~p for compile-time route checks

Introduction to Testing

Requirement: This guide expects that you have gone through the introductory guides and got a Phoenix application up and running.

Testing has become integral to the software development process, and the ability to easily write meaningful tests is an indispensable feature for any modern web framework. Phoenix takes this seriously, providing support files to make all the major components of the framework easy to test. It also generates test modules with real-world examples alongside any generated modules to help get us going.

Elixir ships with a built-in testing framework called ExUnit. ExUnit strives to be clear and explicit, keeping magic to a minimum. Phoenix uses ExUnit for all of its testing, and we will use it here as well.

Running tests

When Phoenix generates a web application for us, it also includes tests. To run them, simply type mix test:

$ mix test
....

Finished in 0.09 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 652656

We already have five tests!

In fact, we already have a directory structure completely set up for testing, including a test helper and support files.

test
├── hello_web
│   └── controllers
│       ├── error_html_test.exs
│       ├── error_json_test.exs
│       └── page_controller_test.exs
├── support
│   ├── conn_case.ex
│   └── data_case.ex
└── test_helper.exs

The test cases we get for free include those from test/hello_web/controllers/. They are testing our controllers and views. If you haven't read the guides for controllers and views, now is a good time.

Understanding test modules

We are going to use the next sections to get acquainted with Phoenix testing structure. We will start with the three test files generated by Phoenix.

The first test file we'll look at is test/hello_web/controllers/page_controller_test.exs.

defmodule HelloWeb.PageControllerTest do
  use HelloWeb.ConnCase

  test "GET /", %{conn: conn} do
    conn = get(conn, ~p"/")
    assert html_response(conn, 200) =~ "Peace of mind from prototype to production"
  end
end

There are a couple of interesting things happening here.

Our test files simply define modules. At the top of each module, you will find a line such as:

use HelloWeb.ConnCase

If you were to write an Elixir library, outside of Phoenix, instead of use HelloWeb.ConnCase you would write use ExUnit.Case. However, Phoenix already ships with a bunch of functionality for testing controllers and HelloWeb.ConnCase builds on top of ExUnit.Case to bring these functionalities in. We will explore the HelloWeb.ConnCase module soon.

Then we define each test using the test/3 macro. The test/3 macro receives three arguments: the test name, the testing context that we are pattern matching on, and the contents of the test. In this test, we access the root page of our application by a "GET" HTTP request on the path "/" with the get/2 macro. Then we assert that the rendered page contains the string "Peace of mind from prototype to production".

When writing tests in Elixir, we use assertions to check that something is true. In our case, assert html_response(conn, 200) =~ "Peace of mind from prototype to production" is doing a couple things:

It asserts that conn has rendered a response
It asserts that the response has the 200 status code (which means OK in HTTP parlance)
It asserts that the type of the response is HTML
It asserts that the result of html_response(conn, 200), which is an HTML response, has the string "Peace of mind from prototype to production" in it

However, from where does the conn we use on get and html_response come from? To answer this question, let's take a look at HelloWeb.ConnCase.

The ConnCase

If you open up test/support/conn_case.ex, you will find this (with comments removed):

defmodule HelloWeb.ConnCase do
  use ExUnit.CaseTemplate

  using do
    quote do
      # The default endpoint for testing
      @endpoint HelloWeb.Endpoint

      use HelloWeb, :verified_routes

      # Import conveniences for testing with connections
      import Plug.Conn
      import Phoenix.ConnTest
      import HelloWeb.ConnCase
    end
  end
  
  setup tags do
    Hello.DataCase.setup_sandbox(tags)
    {:ok, conn: Phoenix.ConnTest.build_conn()}
  end
end

There is a lot to unpack here.

The second line says this is a case template. This is a ExUnit feature that allows developers to replace the built-in use ExUnit.Case by their own case. This line is pretty much what allows us to write use HelloWeb.ConnCase at the top of our controller tests.

Now that we have made this module a case template, we can define callbacks that are invoked on certain occasions. The using callback defines code to be injected on every module that calls use HelloWeb.ConnCase. In this case, it starts by setting the @endpoint module attribute with the name of our endpoint.

Next, it wires up :verified_routes to allow us to use ~p based paths in our test just like we do in the rest of our application to easily generate paths and URLs in our tests.

Finally, we import Plug.Conn, so all of the connection helpers available in controllers are also available in tests, and then imports Phoenix.ConnTest. You can consult these modules to learn all functionality available.

Then our case template defines a setup block. The setup block will be called before test. Most of the setup block is on setting up the SQL Sandbox, which we will talk about later. In the last line of the setup block, we will find this:

{:ok, conn: Phoenix.ConnTest.build_conn()}

The last line of setup can return test metadata that will be available in each test. The metadata we are passing forward here is a newly built Plug.Conn. In our test, we extract the connection out of this metadata at the very beginning of our test:

test "GET /", %{conn: conn} do

And that's where the connection comes from! At first, the testing structure does come with a bit of indirection, but this indirection pays off as our test suite grows, since it allows us to cut down the amount of boilerplate.

View tests

The other test files in our application are responsible for testing our views.

The error view test case, test/hello_web/controllers/error_html_test.exs, illustrates a few interesting things of its own.

defmodule HelloWeb.ErrorHTMLTest do
  use HelloWeb.ConnCase, async: true

  # Bring render_to_string/4 for testing custom views
  import Phoenix.Template

  test "renders 404.html" do
    assert render_to_string(HelloWeb.ErrorHTML, "404", "html", []) == "Not Found"
  end

  test "renders 500.html" do
    assert render_to_string(HelloWeb.ErrorHTML, "500", "html", []) == "Internal Server Error"
  end
end

HelloWeb.ErrorHTMLTest sets async: true which means that this test case will be run in parallel with other test cases. While individual tests within the case still run serially, this can greatly increase overall test speeds.

It also imports Phoenix.Template in order to use the render_to_string/4 function. With that, all the assertions can be simple string equality tests.

Running tests per directory/file

Now that we have an idea what our tests are doing, let's look at different ways to run them.

As we saw near the beginning of this guide, we can run our entire suite of tests with mix test.

$ mix test
....

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 540755

If we would like to run all the tests in a given directory, test/hello_web/controllers for instance, we can pass the path to that directory to mix test.

$ mix test test/hello_web/controllers/
.

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 652376

In order to run all the tests in a specific file, we can pass the path to that file into mix test.

$ mix test test/hello_web/controllers/error_html_test.exs
...

Finished in 0.2 seconds
2 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 220535

And we can run a single test in a file by appending a colon and a line number to the filename.

Let's say we only wanted to run the test for the way HelloWeb.ErrorHTML renders 500.html. The test begins on line 11 of the file, so this is how we would do it.

$ mix test test/hello_web/controllers/error_html_test.exs:11
Including tags: [line: "11"]
Excluding tags: [:test]

.

Finished in 0.1 seconds
2 tests, 0 failures, 1 excluded

Randomized with seed 288117

We chose to run this specifying the first line of the test, but actually, any line of that test will do. These line numbers would all work - :11, :12, or :13.

Running tests using tags

ExUnit allows us to tag our tests individually or for the whole module. We can then choose to run only the tests with a specific tag, or we can exclude tests with that tag and run everything else.

Let's experiment with how this works.

First, we'll add a @moduletag to test/hello_web/controllers/error_html_test.exs.

defmodule HelloWeb.ErrorHTMLTest do
  use HelloWeb.ConnCase, async: true

  @moduletag :error_view_case
  ...
end

If we use only an atom for our module tag, ExUnit assumes that it has a value of true. We could also specify a different value if we wanted.

defmodule HelloWeb.ErrorHTMLTest do
  use HelloWeb.ConnCase, async: true

  @moduletag error_view_case: "some_interesting_value"
  ...
end

For now, let's leave it as a simple atom @moduletag :error_view_case.

We can run only the tests from the error view case by passing --only error_view_case into mix test.

$ mix test --only error_view_case
Including tags: [:error_view_case]
Excluding tags: [:test]

...

Finished in 0.1 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 3 excluded

Randomized with seed 125659

Note: ExUnit tells us exactly which tags it is including and excluding for each test run. If we look back to the previous section on running tests, we'll see that line numbers specified for individual tests are actually treated as tags.

$ mix test test/hello_web/controllers/error_html_test.exs:11
Including tags: [line: "11"]
Excluding tags: [:test]

.

Finished in 0.2 seconds
2 tests, 0 failures, 1 excluded

Randomized with seed 364723

Specifying a value of true for error_view_case yields the same results.

$ mix test --only error_view_case:true
Including tags: [error_view_case: "true"]
Excluding tags: [:test]

...

Finished in 0.1 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 3 excluded

Randomized with seed 833356

Specifying false as the value for error_view_case, however, will not run any tests because no tags in our system match error_view_case: false.

$ mix test --only error_view_case:false
Including tags: [error_view_case: "false"]
Excluding tags: [:test]



Finished in 0.1 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 5 excluded

Randomized with seed 622422
The --only option was given to "mix test" but no test executed

We can use the --exclude flag in a similar way. This will run all of the tests except those in the error view case.

$ mix test --exclude error_view_case
Excluding tags: [:error_view_case]

.

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 2 excluded

Randomized with seed 682868

Specifying values for a tag works the same way for --exclude as it does for --only.

We can tag individual tests as well as full test cases. Let's tag a few tests in the error view case to see how this works.

defmodule HelloWeb.ErrorHTMLTest do
  use HelloWeb.ConnCase, async: true

  @moduletag :error_view_case

  # Bring render/4 and render_to_string/4 for testing custom views
  import Phoenix.Template

  @tag individual_test: "yup"
  test "renders 404.html" do
    assert render_to_string(HelloWeb.ErrorView, "404", "html", []) ==
           "Not Found"
  end

  @tag individual_test: "nope"
  test "renders 500.html" do
    assert render_to_string(HelloWeb.ErrorView, "500", "html", []) ==
           "Internal Server Error"
  end
end

If we would like to run only tests tagged as individual_test, regardless of their value, this will work.

$ mix test --only individual_test
Including tags: [:individual_test]
Excluding tags: [:test]

..

Finished in 0.1 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 3 excluded

Randomized with seed 813729

We can also specify a value and run only tests with that.

$ mix test --only individual_test:yup
Including tags: [individual_test: "yup"]
Excluding tags: [:test]

.

Finished in 0.1 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 4 excluded

Randomized with seed 770938

Similarly, we can run all tests except for those tagged with a given value.

$ mix test --exclude individual_test:nope
Excluding tags: [individual_test: "nope"]

...

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 1 excluded

Randomized with seed 539324

We can be more specific and exclude all the tests from the error view case except the one tagged with individual_test that has the value "yup".

$ mix test --exclude error_view_case --include individual_test:yup
Including tags: [individual_test: "yup"]
Excluding tags: [:error_view_case]

..

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 1 excluded

Randomized with seed 61472

Finally, we can configure ExUnit to exclude tags by default. The default ExUnit configuration is done in the test/test_helper.exs file:

ExUnit.start(exclude: [error_view_case: true])

Ecto.Adapters.SQL.Sandbox.mode(Hello.Repo, :manual)

Now when we run mix test, it only runs the specs from our page_controller_test.exs and error_json_test.exs.

$ mix test
Excluding tags: [error_view_case: true]

.

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures, 2 excluded

Randomized with seed 186055

We can override this behavior with the --include flag, telling mix test to include tests tagged with error_view_case.

$ mix test --include error_view_case
Including tags: [:error_view_case]
Excluding tags: [error_view_case: true]

....

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 748424

This technique can be very useful to control very long running tests, which you may only want to run in CI or in specific scenarios.

Randomization

Running tests in random order is a good way to ensure that our tests are truly isolated. If we notice that we get sporadic failures for a given test, it may be because a previous test changes the state of the system in ways that aren't cleaned up afterward, thereby affecting the tests which follow. Those failures might only present themselves if the tests are run in a specific order.

ExUnit will randomize the order tests run in by default, using an integer to seed the randomization. If we notice that a specific random seed triggers our intermittent failure, we can re-run the tests with that same seed to reliably recreate that test sequence in order to help us figure out what the problem is.

$ mix test --seed 401472
....

Finished in 0.2 seconds
5 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 401472

Concurrency and partitioning

As we have seen, ExUnit allows developers to run tests concurrently. This allows developers to use all of the power in their machine to run their test suites as fast as possible. Couple this with Phoenix performance, most test suites compile and run in a fraction of the time compared to other frameworks.

While developers usually have powerful machines available to them during development, this may not always be the case in your Continuous Integration servers. For this reason, ExUnit also supports out of the box test partitioning in test environments. If you open up your config/test.exs, you will find the database name set to:

database: "hello_test#{System.get_env("MIX_TEST_PARTITION")}",

By default, the MIX_TEST_PARTITION environment variable has no value, and therefore it has no effect. But in your CI server, you can, for example, split your test suite across machines by using four distinct commands:

$ MIX_TEST_PARTITION=1 mix test --partitions 4
$ MIX_TEST_PARTITION=2 mix test --partitions 4
$ MIX_TEST_PARTITION=3 mix test --partitions 4
$ MIX_TEST_PARTITION=4 mix test --partitions 4

That's all you need to do and ExUnit and Phoenix will take care of all rest, including setting up the database for each distinct partition with a distinct name.

Going further

While ExUnit is a simple test framework, it provides a really flexible and robust test runner through the mix test command. We recommend you to run mix help test or read the docs online

We've seen what Phoenix gives us with a newly generated app. Furthermore, whenever you generate a new resource, Phoenix will generate all appropriate tests for that resource too. For example, you can create a complete scaffold with schema, context, controllers, and views by running the following command at the root of your application:

$ mix phx.gen.html Blog Post posts title body:text
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_controller.ex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_html/edit.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_html/index.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_html/new.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_html/show.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_html/post_form.html.heex
* creating lib/hello_web/controllers/post_html.ex
* creating test/hello_web/controllers/post_controller_test.exs
* creating lib/hello/blog/post.ex
* creating priv/repo/migrations/20211001233016_create_posts.exs
* creating lib/hello/blog.ex
* injecting lib/hello/blog.ex
* creating test/hello/blog_test.exs
* injecting test/hello/blog_test.exs
* creating test/support/fixtures/blog_fixtures.ex
* injecting test/support/fixtures/blog_fixtures.ex

Add the resource to your browser scope in lib/demo_web/router.ex:

    resources "/posts", PostController


Remember to update your repository by running migrations:

    $ mix ecto.migrate

Now let's follow the directions and add the new resources route to our lib/hello_web/router.ex file and run the migrations.

When we run mix test again, we see that we now have twenty-one tests!

$ mix test
................

Finished in 0.1 seconds
21 tests, 0 failures

Randomized with seed 537537

At this point, we are at a great place to transition to the rest of the testing guides, in which we'll examine these tests in much more detail, and add some of our own.

Using SSL

To prepare an application to serve requests over SSL, we need to add a little bit of configuration and two environment variables. In order for SSL to actually work, we'll need a key file and certificate file from a certificate authority. The environment variables that we'll need are paths to those two files.

The configuration consists of a new https: key for our endpoint whose value is a keyword list of port, path to the key file, and path to the cert (PEM) file. If we add the otp_app: key whose value is the name of our application, Plug will begin to look for them at the root of our application. We can then put those files in our priv directory and set the paths to priv/our_keyfile.key and priv/our_cert.crt.

Here's an example configuration from config/runtime.exs.

import Config

config :hello, HelloWeb.Endpoint,
  http: [port: {:system, "PORT"}],
  url: [host: "example.com"],
  cache_static_manifest: "priv/static/cache_manifest.json",
  https: [
    port: 443,
    cipher_suite: :strong,
    otp_app: :hello,
    keyfile: System.get_env("SOME_APP_SSL_KEY_PATH"),
    certfile: System.get_env("SOME_APP_SSL_CERT_PATH"),
    # OPTIONAL Key for intermediate certificates:
    cacertfile: System.get_env("INTERMEDIATE_CERTFILE_PATH")
  ]

Without the otp_app: key, we need to provide absolute paths to the files wherever they are on the filesystem in order for Plug to find them.

Path.expand("../../../some/path/to/ssl/key.pem", __DIR__)

The options under the https: key are passed to the Plug adapter, typically Bandit, which in turn uses Plug.SSL to select the TLS socket options. Please refer to the documentation for Plug.SSL.configure/1 for more information on the available options and their defaults. The Plug HTTPS Guide and the Erlang/OTP ssl documentation also provide valuable information.

SSL in Development

If you would like to use HTTPS in development, a self-signed certificate can be generated by running: mix phx.gen.cert. This requires Erlang/OTP 20 or later.

With your self-signed certificate, your development configuration in config/dev.exs can be updated to run an HTTPS endpoint:

config :my_app, MyAppWeb.Endpoint,
  ...
  https: [
    port: 4001,
    cipher_suite: :strong,
    keyfile: "priv/cert/selfsigned_key.pem",
    certfile: "priv/cert/selfsigned.pem"
  ]

This can replace your http configuration, or you can run HTTP and HTTPS servers on different ports.

Force SSL

In many cases, you'll want to force all incoming requests to use SSL by redirecting HTTP to HTTPS. This can be accomplished by setting the :force_ssl option in your endpoint configuration. It expects a list of options which are forwarded to Plug.SSL. By default, it sets the "strict-transport-security" header in HTTPS requests, forcing browsers to always use HTTPS. If an unsafe (HTTP) request is sent, it redirects to the HTTPS version using the :host specified in the :url configuration. For example:

config :my_app, MyAppWeb.Endpoint,
  force_ssl: [rewrite_on: [:x_forwarded_proto]]

To dynamically redirect to the host of the current request, set :host in the :force_ssl configuration to nil.

config :my_app, MyAppWeb.Endpoint,
  force_ssl: [rewrite_on: [:x_forwarded_proto], host: nil]

In these examples, the rewrite_on: key specifies the HTTP header used by a reverse proxy or load balancer in front of the application to indicate whether the request was received over HTTP or HTTPS. For more information on the implications of offloading TLS to an external element, in particular relating to secure cookies, refer to the Plug HTTPS Guide. Keep in mind that the options passed to Plug.SSL in that document should be set using the force_ssl: endpoint option in a Phoenix application.

It is important to note that force_ssl: is a compile time config, so it normally is set in prod.exs, it will not work when set from runtime.exs.

HSTS

HSTS, short for 'HTTP Strict-Transport-Security', is a mechanism that allows websites to declare themselves as accessible exclusively through a secure connection (HTTPS). It was introduced to prevent man-in-the-middle attacks that strip SSL/TLS encryption. HSTS causes web browsers to redirect from HTTP to HTTPS and to refuse to connect unless the connection uses SSL/TLS.

With force_ssl: [hsts: true] set, the Strict-Transport-Security header is added with a max-age that defines the duration for which the policy is valid. Modern web browsers will respond to this by redirecting from HTTP to HTTPS, among other consequences. RFC6797, which defines HSTS, also specifies that the browser should keep track of a host's policy and apply it until it expires. It further specifies that traffic on any port other than 80 is assumed to be encrypted as per the policy.

While HSTS is recommended in production, it can lead to unexpected behavior when accessing applications on localhost. For instance, accessing an application with HSTS enabled at https://localhost:4000 leads to a situation where all subsequent traffic from localhost, except for port 80, is expected to be encrypted. This can disrupt traffic to other local servers or proxies running on your computer that are unrelated to your Phoenix application and may not support encrypted traffic.

If you inadvertently enable HSTS for localhost, you may need to reset your browser's cache before it will accept HTTP traffic from localhost again.

For Chrome:

Open the Developer Tools Panel.
Click and hold the reload icon next to the address bar to reveal a dropdown menu.
Select "Empty Cache and Hard Reload".

For Safari:

Clear your browser cache.
Remove the entry from ~/Library/Cookies/HSTS.plist or delete the file entirely.
Restart Safari.

For other browsers, please consult the documentation for HSTS.

Alternatively, setting the :expires option on force_ssl to 0 should expire the entry and disable HSTS.

For more information on HSTS options, see Plug.SSL.